<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mary Magdalen's tears wip't off. Or The voice of peace to an unquiet conscience. Written by way of letter to a person of quality. And published for the comfort of all those, who mourn in Zion.</title>
            <author>Martin, T., 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1913_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202880</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863019</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115201</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89617)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115201)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 237:E1913[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mary Magdalen's tears wip't off. Or The voice of peace to an unquiet conscience. Written by way of letter to a person of quality. And published for the comfort of all those, who mourn in Zion.</title>
                  <author>Martin, T., 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 116, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for T. Garthwait, at the little north-door of S. Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to T. Martin.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Includes half-title.</note>
                  <note>With an added leaf of prayer and a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with J. Courtney's name in imprint.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115201:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115201:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MARY MAGDALEN'S Tears wipt off. OR The VOICE of PEACE TO AN UNQUIET CONSCIENCE.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By Way of Letter TO A PERSON of QUALITY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> Publiſhed for the Comfort of all thoſe, who Mourn in <hi>Zion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>T. Garthwait,</hi> at the Little North-door of S. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115201:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115201:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Publiſher of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, having in his eye no fear of thy diſlike, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of thy applauſe; hath no other ſollicitation, for thy peruſal there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then the opinion he hath, that it may be ſerviceable, to the good of thy Soul. He thinks he ſhall be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a very <hi>charitable miſtake,</hi> if thou findeſt an errour in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture; and thou more obliged to offer, then he to ask thy pardon for it. To preſcribe <hi>preventive</hi> or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuperative</hi> medicines, in a <hi>great
<pb facs="tcp:115201:3"/>Plague-time,</hi> is no piece of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent officiouſneſs,</hi> but a <hi>prudent diſcharge</hi> of <hi>duty</hi> to the Publick. If thou be ſo <hi>whole, as not to need a Phyſitian;</hi> thou haſt had good luck, having lived in ſo <hi>licentious</hi> an age, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>children that are Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Give <hi>God</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>Grace,</hi> and deſpiſe not the good wiſhes of thy <hi>Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115201:3"/>
            <head>A Short TABLE of the principall Contents in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the Secret and Revealed will in God. &amp;c. page <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Day of Grace being ſpent. page <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Sins of Ignorance and Wilfulneſs. page <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Preſumptuous Sins. page <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Sins after Baptiſme. page <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of want of Sorrow for Sin. page <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Gods accepting Mens Perſons. page <hi>29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Perſonall Aſſurance. page <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Sacerdotall Abſolution, and Gods Ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. page <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Eſau</hi> ſeeking the Bleſſing, &amp;c. page <hi>50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Example of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that provoked God <hi>Ten</hi> times in the Wilderneſs. page <hi>52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Aſſurance of Salvation. page <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Witneſs</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the Spirit. page <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Combat between the Fleſh, and the Spirit. page <hi>63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Motions to Sin in Regenerate perſons. page <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of perfect and unſinning Obedience. page <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Meaſure of well doing in Holy and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Actions, as in Prayer, Alms, Faſting. page <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. Math. <hi>19.12. He that is able to Receive it, &amp;c.</hi> whether an Advice, &amp;c, page <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:115201:4"/>
               <item>Of <hi>Loving the Lord with all our Soul, &amp;c.</hi> and not doing <hi>every thing</hi> we have ability to do. page <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Doing Holy and Vertuous Actions in the want of Charity. page <hi>92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of making a mans ſelf the end of his Actions. page <hi>59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt the Fear of Death. page <hi>98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Falling away from Grace. page <hi>103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Converſion. page <hi>105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Relapſes into Sin, and Injection of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thoughts. page <hi>107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Want of Children. page <hi>112</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115201:4"/>
            <head>MARY MAGDALEN'S Tears wip't off, OR The VOICE of PEACE <hi>To an Unquiet Conſcience.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thank you for your Charity to me, in <hi>calling</hi> me to my Prayers, and ſhall by Gods Grace, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to requite it, by a <hi>counter-change</hi> of Charity, in praying for you, as you have deſired me. I cannot ſay, that I am ſorrie that you ſtand in need of being <hi>prayed for:</hi> we all do <hi>ſo,</hi> and they moſt of all, and the more for that, who think they <hi>need</hi> not <hi>other mens prayers:</hi> But <hi>Madam,</hi> as I cannot but admire your Humility in this pious requeſt, (whoſe gracious Heart, like the <hi>Treaſurie</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> accepts of <hi>Mites</hi> as well as <hi>Talents</hi>) ſo, I am not a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of mine own indigence, and empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and (which is worſt of all) of my own
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115201:5"/>unworthineſs. I ſpeak it in good earneſt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> and being by your <hi>call</hi> for my prayers become very ſenſible of my unfitneſs, at leaſt for the <hi>Interceſſional</hi> part of that duty; I can aſſure my ſelf, that as I truſt you will not be the <hi>worſe;</hi> ſo ſhall I be much the <hi>better,</hi> for my <hi>praying</hi> for you.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Madam,</hi> for my prayers only, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume you did not ſend me that <hi>Summons:</hi> I cannot then but eſteem my ſelf obliged, to render a duty to you, of the ſame impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; but more immediately tending to the production of that effect, which you have deſired me to pray for; and which (perhaps) if more <hi>timely,</hi> and <hi>individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> applyed, the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> had not been ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate, and raging as it is; nor you ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtful of the vertue and efficacie of <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> as you are.</p>
            <p>By ſome ſcattered expreſſions of my <hi>Friend,</hi> that delivered your meſſage to me, I very confidently ſuſpect your languiſhing under the waſting torment of a <hi>wounded Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> but How long, by what cauſe, or upon what occaſion; I have no hint, upon which I may reaſonably ground a Preſumption. So innocent hath been that <hi>Act</hi> of your Life, of which I have been a <hi>Spectator;</hi> ſo rational, cloſe, and undiſtracted your diſcourſe; that I dare confidently affirm, no <hi>Indications</hi> of this ſecret <hi>Maladie</hi> did ever preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the moſt acute obſerver of your
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115201:5"/>Converſation with us. My thoughts concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch a State in general, I have judged it my duty to deliver; but how pertinent, or conducent to the removal of the particular cauſe of your trouble, I am not able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; for the reaſons before mentioned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Soul of man comes out of the hands of her Creator, like a rich and curious Watch; carrying in her ſelf, as the Cauſes of her own motion; ſo no diſorder, till ſhe fall under unskilful, or unruly fingers. Her firſt immerſion into the Bodie, renders her not only lyable to the guilt of Original ſin, but to the future turbulencies, and exceſſes of thoſe faculties common to us and Beaſts: which, becauſe in them govern'd only by an uncontroulable inſtinct of nature, are wholly ſinleſs, and have in them no other tendency, but the preſervation of that creature in which they work: but with man it is much other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; whoſe appetites are ſubjected to a rational choice, under the penalty exacted by a Law, wholly commenſurate with reaſon, and the noble dictates of a Soul, emancipated from the Suggeſtions, and deluſions of fleſh and blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence is it that ſhe receives in us no wounds, but by our own hands: her Peace is never broken, but by Errours in our Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that moſt times but radically nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the true reſentment of our guilt and danger, being ſubſequent to a reflexive act of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115201:6"/>the Soul; from whence proceed thoſe <hi>Smiting Thoughts,</hi> able to wear out, or rend an heart of <hi>Adamant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſource or ſpring whereof uſually are the conſideration either 1. of what we have been; or of 2. what we are; or of 3. what we ſhall or may be hereafter; the guilt of ſin acted, the prevalency of ſinful diſpoſitions in our nature, and of enormous habits in our perſons; the fear of Relapſes, and horrour of future puniſhments, are that which ſet mens ſouls upon <hi>Tenter hooks:</hi> and few there be, who have been guilty of any groſs ſin, whoſe Prepentance (if true) hath not given them ſome taſte of this bitter Cup, apporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate to the courſe of their unregenerate life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What we have been] is of the ſame la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in our Regeneration, from whence we are to compute our <hi>Spiritual life;</hi> as in our Creation, from whence we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive our <hi>Natural being.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22.</note> As from <hi>Adam all lived,</hi> ſo <hi>in Adam all dyed: all dead in Sins and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes: God hath concluded all under ſin, that he might have mercy upon all.</hi> Only the Difference is in the circumſtances, ſome greater, ſome leſſer ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners then others: ſome longer, others leſſe while dead in ſins and Treſpaſſes: but the danger, without repentance, is the ſame to the ſinner; the Cure the ſame to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115201:6"/>To him the ſame thing, to raiſe <hi>Jairus</hi> daughter to life, yet ſcarcely cold <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.22. as to bring <hi>Lazarus</hi>'s ſtinking carcaſe out of his grave, <hi>John</hi> 11.43. Both ſupernatural works, and a ſupernatural Worker required to both: yet both effected without any <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion</hi> of the power by which it was done, becauſe inſinitely able to work.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But as ſome of thoſe blinde men, whom our Saviour reſtored to ſight, ſaw at the very firſt as perfectly, as ever after: but others when their eyes were firſt opened, <hi>ſaw men as Trees walking, Mark</hi> 8.24. ſo are not the ſame apprehenſions of their ſpiritual eſtate to all <hi>Penitents;</hi> though <hi>equally</hi> reſtored to Grace, and favour with God, and <hi>Federally</hi> juſtified from the guilt of <hi>paſt</hi> Sins. The Cauſes hereof are various, ariſing partly from the <hi>Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>acquaſite</hi> temper of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons themſelves; partly from ſome errors in ſuch, who applyed to them the <hi>outward means,</hi> and <hi>miniſtration</hi> of their Repentance; partly from ſome <hi>outward accidents</hi> of life; and partly from the <hi>Suggeſtions,</hi> and <hi>Deluſions of Satan,</hi> with ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Some perſons are naturally more apt to impreſſions of Sadneſs, Fear, and Diſtruſt, then are others. Penetrating and quick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of danger, once certainly incurr'd, render ſome <hi>weak ſpirits</hi> diſtruſtful of their ſafety a long time after, be it never ſo ſure and viſible: like men ſtartled out of Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115201:7"/>and frightful dreams, who although awake, cannot preſently be perſwaded, that they are free from peril. The very apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the danger, his churliſhneſs and folly had caſt him into, made <hi>Nabals</hi> heart <hi>dic</hi> within him. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.37.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denyed by the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that the guilt of ſin once truly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, with all the conſequents of horrour it draws after it, is able to ſink a very clear and ſerene ſoul, into an <hi>Alyſſe</hi> of black, and ſad thoughts: from which nothing is able to <hi>buoy,</hi> and raiſe it up; but the light of Gods countenance, ſhining upon, and influencing <hi>that ſpirit,</hi> by <hi>forcible</hi> aſſiſtances of Grace. But yet moſt evident it is, that the <hi>mourning</hi> of ſome Chriſtians is like that of <hi>Rachel,</hi> they will not be comforted: yea ſo predominant in them, ſometimes, is that torpid and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive humour; that it converts comforts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, into matter of diſcomfort: the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, patience, and long-ſuffering of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, together with his unfeigned offers of mercy, and pardon to all that truly turn unto him, (thoſe high and excellent <hi>Cordials</hi> for ſoul-ſick Chriſtians) being by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices of a <hi>miſguided Imagination,</hi> corrupted into moſt bitter jealouſies, either againſt God or themſelves.</p>
            <p>Sometimes their ſpiritual troubles ſpring from the paſſions or unskilfulneſs of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,</hi> under which ſuch perſons live: who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115201:7"/>either wanting the ſagacity, dexterity, (or which is moſt to be feared) the Charity of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 19.20, 22. <hi>to become all things to all men;</hi> eſpecially in that moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and wholſome branch of it, the <hi>being weak with them who are weak,</hi> in the Flock of Chriſt; thunder out the threatnings of the Goſpel, <hi>promiſcuouſly</hi> in the ears of all; <hi>making their hearts ſad, whom God hath not made ſad, Ezek.</hi> 13.22. and ſo <hi>vexing them whom God hath wounded, Pſal.</hi> 69.27. inſtead of calling, encouraging and comforting ſinners under Repentance <hi>(that ſmall and ſtill voice)</hi> terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying them with the Menaces of the Law, <hi>(that loud and furious winde)</hi> and caſting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men ſtrong ſuſpitions of their having e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſed the time of mercy; ſeeming to ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the <hi>great and terrible day of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord,</hi> by taking the ſentence of condemnation out of his mouth. Not conſidering, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel have their Commiſſions dated from <hi>Sion,</hi> and not from <hi>Sinai;</hi> and that the method, and language of S <hi>Paul</hi> in the Pulpit, is not only more ſuitable to that Meſſage of Peace, but moſt imitable by us; becauſe it proved ſo ſucceſsful, in the buſineſs of <hi>Reconciling men to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know that a <hi>Son of Thunder</hi> may have much ſaid on his behalf, from theſe evil and deaf times in which we live: <hi>to lift up the voice like a trumpet, and to ſhew the people their tranſgreſſions, and the houſe of Jacob their ſins,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115201:8"/>Iſai.</hi> 8.1 is a dutie, ſtrongly and indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly lying on a Miniſter of the Goſpel at all times, much more in ſuch an age as this we live in; wherein ſo many thouſands of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>hold the truth of God in unrighteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 1 18. and <hi>turn his Grace into wantonneſs, Jud.</hi> 4. juſtifying not only <hi>Samaria,</hi> but <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and her <hi>Siſters;</hi> by outballancing her, and them, in all manner of <hi>carnal,</hi> and <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> pollutions: but that we ſpeak is <hi>moſtly</hi> againſt the undue care of ſome <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Goſpel, not ſufficiently <hi>heeding</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminating</hi> ſuch, who mourn in <hi>Zion, Eze.</hi> 9.4. upon whoſe foreheads <hi>Ezekiels</hi> mark hath paſt, and againſt whom the ſeverities of thoſe Comminations ought not to be uſed.</p>
            <p>Sometimes this <hi>Trouble of minde,</hi> (if it doth not wholly ſpring, yet) receiveth much ſtrength and nouriſhment, from ſome <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> of life. Every unuſual circumſtance in providential diſpenſations, in the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſuch men, carries with it the Shape and Terror of <hi>Divine Revenge:</hi> and all lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving corrections, of a moſt wiſe and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Father,</hi> are reckoned upon, as the <hi>ſad Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages</hi> of everlaſting Torments. Nothing but the angry frowns of a terrible Judge, flame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Torches, Fire and Brimſtone, are the <hi>Sceanes</hi> and <hi>Phantaſms</hi> of ſuch clowded brains: yea, ſo ſullen and diſtruſtful, is the Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſuch men, that they ſuſpect every bleſſing, and good thing, that God beſtows
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115201:8"/>upon them in this world, as ſo many <hi>golden Balls</hi> caſt out before them, to betray them in their <hi>Race.</hi> They eat, drink, ſleep, converſe with ſuch anxiety of Spirit, that they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by become intollerable to themſelves and others. Again,</p>
            <p>Satan moſt times hath a deep hand in theſe troubles; who being unchangeably malitious toward mankinde, inceſſantly diſturbs the Peace of ſuch Chriſtians whom he cannot ruine. Yet ſo ſecret and cloſe are his <hi>Devices,</hi> that many prudent Chriſtians are not able (as indeed it is very difficult) to diſcern, betwixt his <hi>injections,</hi> and the <hi>motions</hi> of their own <hi>Appetites.</hi> By which error Satan exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly troubles their quiet, and ſets them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perpetual quarrels againſt themſelves, whereby he thinks it not impoſſible, at laſt to <hi>ingulph</hi> them in <hi>Deſpair.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this may be added, that ſome <hi>Falſe Principles</hi> have in them a very immediate tendency to beget trouble in mens mindes, who are of <hi>inſtable judgments,</hi> but yet of a <hi>good and ingenuous diſpoſition:</hi> thoſe eſpecially concerning the <hi>Irreſiſtibility of ſaving Grace,</hi> the <hi>neceſſity of ones believing himſelf to be Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, unconditionate Election to Salvation,</hi> with ſome others, whoſe falſity is plainly demonſtrated, by many excellent <hi>Treatiſes</hi> of learned, judicious, and pious <hi>Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it a conſideration impertinent to the matter in hand, that there is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115201:9"/>worthy our obſervation, betwixt Sin in the <hi>Memory,</hi> and in the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of a ſinner; the not perception whereof, may cauſe great trouble, and diſquiet in mens mindes. For as the <hi>Conſcience</hi> and the <hi>Memory</hi> are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally one and the ſame thing; ſo neither is ſin to be accounted of the ſame <hi>concernment</hi> to the ſinner, when it is only repreſented by the <hi>Memory,</hi> and when charged upon him by his <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Uſually, proportionable to the meaſure of our <hi>Faith and Repentance</hi> is our Peace of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> by theſe are the Marks and Characters of our guilt purged away by degrees: but the <hi>tranſient Act</hi> of ſin commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is ever recollected by the <hi>Memory,</hi> appor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionately to the natural vigour of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in every man. And from hence it is, that in the fourfold diſtinction of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> there is one ſort which is ſaid to be <hi>good,</hi> but not <hi>quiet:</hi> which (for my own part) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be an <hi>effect,</hi> produced betwixt the <hi>memorative</hi> and <hi>imaginative</hi> faculties; rather then a true, and diſtinct ſtate of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in a Chriſtian; it being, to my underſtanding, equally poſſible for the <hi>Imagination,</hi> to act and perſonate <hi>Conſcience</hi> (in ſome men) as well in the <hi>punitive</hi> and <hi>vindicative,</hi> as in the <hi>affirmative</hi> and <hi>interpretative</hi> power of Law. Where the <hi>Imagination</hi> (as conſcience) may <hi>make Law</hi> to govern mens actions, as in <hi>ſome</hi> it confeſſedly doth: it is not diſproportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſteaſon to believe, that <hi>Imagination</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115201:9"/>may likewiſe perplex, and puniſh <hi>thoſe men,</hi> for the breach of ſuch <hi>Laws,</hi> as likewiſe <hi>Conſcience</hi> doth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But let the Cauſes and <hi>Occaſions</hi> of theſe <hi>Diſtempers</hi> be what they will; be it the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> or <hi>imaginative Faculty,</hi> or <hi>Memory,</hi> or <hi>all,</hi> or any other thing, that procures, or promotes this trouble; uſually, theſe are the effects thereof, in ſad reiterated Objections.</p>
            <div n="1" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION I.</head>
               <p>My Sins are not as other mens, they are not the <hi>Spots of Gods Children:</hi> they have theſe Circumſtances, that render them moſt formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable. They are <hi>1.</hi> more then other mens, <hi>2.</hi> greater, <hi>3.</hi> more loved, <hi>4.</hi> longer lived in, <hi>5.</hi> leſs grieved for, then the Sins of other men.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="6">6. PUt all theſe Circumſtances together, but the laſt (which ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by it ſelf) your ſins can be but great, many, loved, relapſed, and perhaps after ſharp Corrections for them, Vows againſt them, ſence of ſtrength and ability through grace, to oppoſe, reſiſt, and overcome them, and all the moſt powerful temptations to them, and this acknowledged, and owned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115201:10"/>by your ſelf, in your impaſſionate, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate thoughts.</p>
                  <p>Now what hinders the Remiſsion of ſuch Sins? are theſe the firſt <hi>Scarlet ſins</hi> that have ever been brought before the <hi>Throne of Grace,</hi> to receive another <hi>tincture</hi> by the hands of Mercy and pardon? is there any incapacity in the Sinner, any defect in the means, any qualification in the ſins themſelves, any barre or obſtacle to the Judge, that theſe ſins, that ſuch a ſinner ſhould not be remitted?</p>
                  <p>What makes you uncapable of Pardon? any <hi>Decree</hi> concerning your perſon, in Gods <hi>ſecret Will?</hi> in his <hi>revealed Will</hi> there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> offered to you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to <hi>all that truly repent and turn unto him, Ezek.</hi> 18.21, 22. but if you ſuſpect the <hi>Will of Gods purpoſe,</hi> what he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined concerning your Perſon, in that <hi>Will.</hi> you muſt know, that as there are not two <hi>Wills</hi> in the <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> nor two <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory Acts</hi> of one and the ſame <hi>Will:</hi> So may you aſſure your ſelf, that what may directly be concluded from his <hi>Revealed Will</hi> concerning the ſalvation of mankinde, you have your <hi>joynt-intereſt</hi> therein, with the reſt of the <hi>Redeemed World:</hi> and that no <hi>Decree</hi> hath from all eternity been paſt againſt you, whereby a barre is ſet againſt all your good and ſquare endeavours, and your perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected into a <hi>fatal neceſſity</hi> of being damned. Impoſſible indeed it is that ſuch <hi>dormant At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainders</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115201:10"/>ſhould lye againſt the Perſons of ſome men, for the Prevarication and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of our firſt Parents, and yet that <hi>General Act</hi> of the <hi>Grace and Favour of Almighty God,</hi> be ſo <hi>ſolemnly proclaimed</hi> by that great <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador</hi> of our <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION II.</head>
               <p>But I have made my ſelf <hi>uncapable</hi> by loſing the opportunities, and heretofore <hi>deſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſing</hi> both the inward, and outward means of my <hi>Calling,</hi> and therefore juſtly is that fallen upon me, foretold and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in, <hi>Prov. 1.24. Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regarded, &amp;c.</hi> v. <hi>26. I will laugh at your Calamity, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="7">7. IF by the <hi>Opportunity</hi> or <hi>Seaſon</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting unto Salvation, you mean one <hi>point</hi> of time, wherein God doth <hi>ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently once for all,</hi> or <hi>as the laſt tendrie thereof,</hi> not only offer us the <hi>means</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>ſufficiently prepare</hi> and <hi>diſpoſe</hi> the Will to receive it: I doubt not, but that anſwer of our Saviour to his Diſciples, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.7. will be very applyable to you, <hi>It is not for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115201:11"/>you to know the times or the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his own power.</hi> As Grace it ſelf is the <hi>free</hi> and <hi>undeſerved guift</hi> of God, ſo are the <hi>circumſtances</hi> of giving it, for time, manner, and meaſure, His; and diſpoſed of according to the <hi>Will of his purpoſe,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you are not made acquainted, nor privie to any determination concerning your ſelf, unleſs you have had, ſome known Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation thereof. I believe that the <hi>Day of grace,</hi> as far as we are able to collect is not <hi>ſhut up;</hi> nor the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> that at our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Baptiſm <hi>roſe upon our Souls, with healing in his Wings,</hi> ſet, and gone down over us, till our life be ended. Some were called at <hi>the eleventh hour,</hi> when there was but one <hi>hour</hi> more to work in: yet by the bountiful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Lord of the Vineyard were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with the <hi>penny, i. e.</hi> everlaſting life, as well as they who <hi>bore the burden and heat of the day, Matth.</hi> 20.9. Sincerity of Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution is pretious in Gods eye: and where ſufficient time to approve the ſame by good works is not allowed; I doubt not of the ſavable ſtate of that ſoul. Yet I do profeſs, not to believe, that ſuch an one ſhall have an equal ſhare of glory, with Saints of the <hi>firſt magnitude;</hi> neither can there in reaſon be ſo comſortable a poſture of minde lookt for in ſuch an one: this being moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Reſult of that experience we have of our own repentance, by bringing forth fruits
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115201:11"/>
                     <hi>worthy</hi> of it; which ought, when time and means permit, to carry in them a due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, to the continuance, and vileneſs of our former unregenerate life.</p>
                  <p>Now, though Almighty God doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time accept the will for the deed, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>irrefragable Temptation-proof Reſolution</hi> of Converſion for all <hi>future actual performances</hi> thereof; as being able to Foreſee, that that man would perform his reſolutions, in caſe God did permit him ſo much time: yet ſhould no man upon this Conſideration, deferre his Repentance, but rather moſt <hi>ſtudiouſly</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the preſent time offered; not only for that this is to be interpreted an affront of the Divine Majeſty, <hi>by turning the Grace of God into wantonneſs;</hi> but for that no man is aſſured, that ever he ſhall have any ſuch <hi>late, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious minute</hi> vouchſafed unto h m; or if it be, can poſſibly have any aſſurance, that he will be true to his word with God, in his Vows and Reſolutions; God alone, with whom all future things are preſent, being able to foreknow the ſoundneſs, and ſteadineſs of ſuch <hi>ſhipwrackt ingagers.</hi> And as theſe depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies are ſeldom ſo ſucceſsful (at leaſt not ſo often) as many men imagine, and in Charity we may very farre hope; ſo would I have them to be eſteemed, as ſuch, which can have no right <hi>Aſpect</hi> upon, nor incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from, the <hi>uſual, regular</hi> Proceedings of the <hi>Divine Majeſty:</hi> but are rather to be layd,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115201:12"/>on the <hi>unpromiſed exceſſes</hi> and <hi>ſuperabundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> of an infinite goodneſs, extending it ſelf to a ſinner, Repenting him of his ſins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the full and free limits of the <hi>firſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> Conceſſion of Pardon: from a Rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on which, as I would not deterre any the moſt grievous offender; whoſe neglects and former Supinity had caſt him on this <hi>little Plank,</hi> in a Sea of Perplexities; ſo do I almoſt aſſure my ſelf, that ſuch a Chriſtian, who dares continue in ſin, upon the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this <hi>ſuperabundance of grace,</hi> ſhall never be partaker thereof; this being a <hi>Pearl</hi> of too incomparable a value, to be caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Swine,</hi> who hath ſo contemptuouſly <hi>trampled</hi> it under his feet.</p>
                  <p>Yet, if you mark it, your Caſe is far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the ſtate of ſuch a man, who hath neglected (ſay deſpiſed) the offers of mercy till the laſt minute of his life, wherein he rather ſnatches after, then imbraces pardon; being more ſenſible of his own danger, then the love of God: for (bleſſed be God) you have not received any <hi>Summons,</hi> to a ſpeedy <hi>account of your ſtewardſhip,</hi> by a decrepid old age, or a violent diſeaſe, or other contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency; but have made it your bleſſed choice, to <hi>double your Pace</hi> in the wayes of Holineſs; having yet, (as far as we are able to gueſs) the <hi>Poſtmeridian</hi> part of your <hi>Day</hi> before you; time enough by the good bleſſing of God, to finiſh your <hi>Task</hi> which is ſet you, <hi>ere
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115201:12"/>the night come wherein no man can work, Jo.</hi> 9.4.</p>
                  <p>As for your <hi>Deſpightfully uſing the Spirit of Grace,</hi> Heb. 10.29. (as you phraſe it after St. <hi>Paul</hi>) an expreſsion more ſuitable to a ſtate of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> than <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregeneracy,</hi> (as you would have me ſuppoſe yours to be) as in your former courſe of life, you ſet (if I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your ſelf) too little an eſteem, upon the wayes of God (the manner of unregent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men:) ſo have you now too bitter a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure upon your own, the ſins of our unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate life, being after converſion, by all <hi>Divines</hi> (I preſume) accounted araungable, under the ſtyle of Infirmities; and therefore of what ſort ſoever, yet pardonable upon Repentance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>I grant (ſay you) that it may be with ſome Chriſtians as with St. <hi>Paul;</hi> he was a moſt violent Perſecutor of the Church, but then it was in a ſtate of <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Unbelief,</hi> and therefore he ſayes, <hi>God had mercy upon him, becauſe he did it through Ignorance, and in Infidelity:</hi> From whence 'tis eaſy to in infer, that had St. <hi>Paul maliciouſly</hi> and <hi>knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115201:13"/>acted thoſe outrages against the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he had undoubtedly been excluded from all hopes of Pardon; What think you then will become of me, <hi>Who knew the will of my Maſter and did it not.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="8">8. THat Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did Ignorantly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Church of <hi>Christ</hi> is unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; and that if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had done the ſame Knowingly, and Maliciouſly, he had not had any grounds to expect Pardon may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably enough be true; but I do not take it to be out of all Queſtion, but the Inference from hence againſt your ſelf is <hi>Illogical,</hi> and will by no means follow upon thoſe <hi>Premiſes.</hi> For thus your Argument ſtands, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had mercy from God for perſecuting the Church of <hi>Chriſt Ignorantly,</hi> therefore who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever committeth any ſin <hi>againſt Conſcience and Knowledge</hi> ſhall not have mercy, and ſuch ſins I am guilty of.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not ſtand to ſhew you the <hi>falſity</hi> of this way of reaſoning, but only diſcover unto you how erroneous your Principles are, and that ſo evidently, as I need not torture you into a confeſsion thereof; Do you profeſs to believe that there is an equality in all kinds of Sin? that Adultery is not a greater ſin than Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Murder or Idolatry than Sabboth breach?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115201:13"/>Rebellion than Theft? I am aſſured you are not involved in this groſs error. But then do you believe, that that circumſtance [of doing it Knowingly] can render the ſame ſin unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable, which if done Ignorantly will upon Repentance undoubtedly be forgiven. <hi>Who then can be ſaved?</hi> What were the ſins of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and of Saint <hi>Peter?</hi> were they not ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Knowledge, yet Repentance reſtor'd both of them to their former ſtation in Gods favour, you cannot ſuppoſe that thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with whom our Saviour converſt, were all of them Sinners only out of Ignorance: <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> was never held to be <hi>Ignorant</hi> (much leſs to be <hi>Inculpably</hi> ſo,) that her courſe of Life was not agreeable to the Law of God: yet ſo dear was ſhe to our Saviour, upon her hearty Repentance, <hi>That after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection he appeared firſt to</hi> Mary Magdalene, <hi>out of whom be had cast ſeven Devils,</hi> Mar. 16.9.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION IV.</head>
               <p>But under the Law the Soul that did ought <hi>preſumptuouſly,</hi> was to be cut off from <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>WE are not under the Law but under Grace,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115201:14"/>that a main branch of that Priviledge is, <hi>That by Him,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Chriſt</hi>) <hi>all that believe are juſtified from all things, from which Ye</hi> (i. e. <hi>the Jews</hi>) <hi>could not be juſtified by the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.39. from whence 'tis clear, that Remiſsion of ſins is given to all Sinners, who repent and believe the Goſpel. Beſides, every ſin that a man commits againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is not a ſin of <hi>Preſumption,</hi> or a ſin committed with an <hi>high Hand;</hi> Preſumption is not an error of, or in the Underſtanding, but in the Will; at leaſt is much more fixt in the Will, than in the intellectual faculty, and therefore to ſin againſt Knowledge, and to ſin Preſumptuouſly are not convertible, and the ſame thing; Preſumption being not only the higheſt degree of Wilfullneſs, and very properly plac'd under the v ce of <hi>Auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city;</hi> but it reflects more upon the perſon of the Law-maker, than on the Law it ſelf; and the contempt of perſons in Authority is ever more grievouſly puniſhed than the breach of ſuch Laws and conſtitutions, as are made by them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION V.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to relapſe into ſin, after not only Reſolutti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but Vows againſt it, as they who ſin after Baptiſm do, is intollerable and a ſign of one
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115201:14"/>that hath forfeited the Grace, that is given him, and is <hi>judicially hardned</hi> by God.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="10">10. TO ſin, and to relapſe into ſin after a Vow againſt it, is that thing indeed which every baptiſed Chriſtian doth: and in thoſe who are <hi>Adult,</hi> or at years of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (not invincibly ignorant of their Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) is infallibly not only a very great Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of ſin, but a ſin it ſelf: and ſuch an Offendour is (in very truth) not only a great Diſhonor to the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but a great <hi>ſcandol</hi> to the <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> diſ-inherited (and that actually) of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the Kingdom of Chriſt, whileſt he continues in that ſtate of Impenitency: but when the courſe is broken, the caſe is quite the contrary; and the <hi>Prodigal</hi> returning, capable of as benign and as hoſpital a <hi>Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in his Fathers houſe, as was that other Son, able to boaſt of his good demeanour from his Childhood. This is the caſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant Sinners, and for ſuch it is, that when they (nay though but a ſingle one) return, <hi>There is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God.</hi> Luke 15.12.</p>
                  <p>But for the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ow in the Baptiſme,</hi> I am not for the preſent) of opinion, that it is any aggravation of ſin, till the baptiſed Perſon comes to years of Diſcretion, and hath ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115201:15"/>actually taken upon him the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his <hi>Baptiſmal vow,</hi> or elſe hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd ſo much knowledge of his Profeſsion, as that he hath, or may have information, that he was initiated thereinto, and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted under ſuch a <hi>ſolemn Stipulation.</hi> But when <hi>I</hi> ſpeak of <hi>Actual</hi> taking upon him the performance of this Vow, I do not mean that ſolemn, direct, oral, and publick tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Obligation on himſelf in <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Confirmation:</hi> but alſo the doing any Chriſtian duty of Communion, whereby he doth (though but <hi>implicitely</hi>) own his Faith, and conſequently his Obligation thereto, made on his behalf by <hi>Suretyes</hi> in his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
                  <p>And again, you muſt conceive, that every willfull ſin againſt Knowledge and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (even in thoſe who are <hi>adult,</hi> and have Actually put themſelves under the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Vow) is no <hi>abdication</hi> of our Vow in Baptiſme, neither do I apprehend that Perſon which ſo offends to be guilty of Perjury, upon every Act of ſuch ſin of Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs, no more than I believe, that every ſingle diſobedience of her Husband may be interpreted to be a perjury in the Wife, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe hath promiſed, and ſolemnly vowed to obey him in the <hi>Mariage Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I confeſs, that an habitual courſe of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſin, in ſuch as do own their profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115201:15"/>nay that any ſin preſumptuouſly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> doth imply a breach of this <hi>vow,</hi> as well as final <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> yea that the abnegation of any evident <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental</hi> of Religion, as <hi>the Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> the Doctrine of the ever <hi>bleſſed and holy Trinity,</hi> (after <hi>firſt and ſecond Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Tit. 3.10. &amp;c. is) a breach of the Vow in Baptiſme, but that every Act of willfull ſin is ſuch, is to my Apprehenſion no more a truth, than for a Chriſtian of the Proteſtant perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to deny <hi>Chriſts local deſcention into Hell,</hi> (which hath no undenyable ground in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) and for that error (for to that <hi>Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> the Church is not infallible) to be held guilty of perjury in breaking, the <hi>ſecond</hi> clauſe, or branch of this Vow in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring him to <hi>believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith,</hi> as well as doth the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>third,</hi> exact from him a <hi>forſaking of the Devil, the World, the Fleſh, and the keeping of Gods holy Will and commandements all the days of my life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But let the moſt that you fear be granted, &amp; you be held guilty of as many perjuries, as you committed other ſins, and this not only in your own eſteem, but in the opinions of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Divines,</hi> yet ſtill this may render that condition to be more lamented, but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make it irrecoverable; for is there any thing in Scripture more frequent than Gods Meſſages by his Prophets to the People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> calling them to repentance, &amp; that after
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115201:16"/>
                     <hi>Covenant-breach,</hi> and promiſing them pardon if they would repent, and convert unto him? The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> may ſuperſede your ſearching any other Scriptures to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe who indeed is abundant in thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Mercy, and therefore a Book very fit to comfort every penitent Soul, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as fit by reaſon of the Threatnings therein to convert the Impenitent.</p>
                  <p>As for that you ſpeak concerning <hi>judicial induration,</hi> or Gods hardening mens hearts in Judg ement;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.28. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.18.</note> I confeſs, that there is a taking away the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> from the ſloathfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, a withdrawing of Grace from him that doth not uſe it, to that end for which it was given him by God: but that ſuch a judgement is not (ordinarily) revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſave by the treaſuring up of wrath againſt the day of wrath, the final impenitence of him who is thus <hi>judicially</hi> hardened by God, will be difficult to prove, there being no very ſure example of this <hi>Induration</hi> in Scripture, ſave that of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> in whom thoſe conſequents were moſt viſible, and of thoſe obſtinate and incredulous <hi>Jews</hi> to whom our Saviour preach'd, or in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, or Country he wrought ſo many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, mentioned in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.14, 15. but that you are in danger of ſuch <hi>judicial</hi> Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as this, is a very remote fear, and to my judgment wholly inconſiſtent with your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Chriſtian Deportment.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="objection">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115201:16"/>
               <head>OBJECTION.</head>
               <p>But you ſay, my Sins are confeſſedly very great, (being accompanyed with ſuch circumſtances as they are) even withall the <hi>Allowances</hi> your Charity or Judgement can afford them: they cannot then but require a proportionable Grief for them, which as yet I find not in my ſelf; <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod that drew water from Rocks of the Wilderneſs, being not able to break and wound my ſtony Heart into Rivers of Tears, ſuch as are fit to cleanſe and wrince away theſe ſtains of Sin.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION VI.</head>
                  <p n="11">11. THis complaint is but a retrive of one of thoſe <hi>Aggravations</hi> of your ſins men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by you at the firſt, and by me deferred to be ſatisfied at that time. I ſay therefore that it cannot be denyed, but that Grief for ſin committed ought to bear ſome proportion with the heinouſneſs of our Crimes for which we deſire to grieve and lament: but you may be very unfit to judge of this proportion; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing your <hi>Grief</hi> and <hi>Revenge,</hi> with an intermixture of other <hi>Iraſcible paſsions,</hi> hath made you already too obnoxious to the <hi>devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115201:17"/>of Satan, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. and <hi>Peter</hi> three times denyed that he knew his Maſter, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.66. and that with Curſings and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>Imprecations</hi> (perhaps) upon himſelf if he knew any <hi>ſuch man, Luk.</hi> 22.55. Here was a Complication of very groſs ſins, as Swearing, Curſing, Denyal of his Maſter, whom lately he profeſſed to be the <hi>Son of God;</hi> and all this a flat Perjury; yet you never read of Tears ſhed for theſe Sins more then once:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.75. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.72. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.62.</note> but then they are recorded to be <hi>Bitter</hi> ones, what they wanted in the <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Proportion to the Standard of mans Judgement, they had in the <hi>Intrinſick</hi> value, moſt proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Judgement of God.</p>
                  <p>You muſt know then, that Grief and Shame, and ſuch like <hi>Affections</hi> of the <hi>Iraſcible Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite,</hi> are parts of that <hi>corrective</hi> Juſtice, which we execute upon our ſelves; and very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly on the <hi>lower Soul,</hi> becauſe that hath been moſt inſtrumental in our Sins, and hath likewiſe had the greateſt ſhare of the Senſual Pleaſure received in ſinning; as alſo for that ſhe is the moſt proper inſtrument to macerate and chaſtize the Body, (the other <hi>Aſſociate</hi> and <hi>Conſpirator</hi> in offending.) That which ought to give the greateſt ſatisfaction to the Penitent, concerning the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> of his Sorrow for Sin, is the Averſation of his <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Minde</hi> to <hi>all</hi> former evil wayes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115201:17"/>as ſuch; with a full Reſolution, and ſincere Endeavour, to avoid and fly <hi>all</hi> Sin for the time to come, and to imbrace and practiſe moſt impartially, <hi>all</hi> Rules of <hi>Godlineſs, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Sobriety,</hi> at what rate ſoever he purchaſe the performance of them; facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating his way thereto, by a frequent and prudent exerciſe of ſuch helps of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as his Lord and Maſter Chriſt, and the Church his Mother, have recommended by example, or enjoyned by Precept.</p>
                  <p>Neither is there any cauſe to complain, that theſe <hi>Severe Courſes</hi> are not reconcilea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a cheerful manner of living in this World, ſo far as not to caſt any torpid Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhments on our frail Bodies, or to render our ſelves complyable with ſober and honeſt Converſation: for they who have, and daily do make Tryal of theſe <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> for a Chriſtian mans life, do not finde ſo much trouble in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e practice of them, as in the <hi>ſad Reflections</hi> on their former Unregenerate State; which yet they may now contemplate with Glory to God, and Comfort to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who through the Grace of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> hath given them the Victory over ſo Unwearied, ſo Politick, and ſo Powerful Enemies to their ſalvation: if Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can perſwade you, that it is matter of Sadneſs for a man to paſs through rough and dirty wayes, that he may in ſhort time go and be poſſeſt of a Kingdom; or if you can
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115201:18"/>imagine, that that man hath reaſonable cauſe of Complaint, who is ſure to eſcape the Bloody Hands of <hi>Aſſaſſines,</hi> if he will but take the pains to <hi>Winde</hi> himſelf after a ſure <hi>Guide,</hi> through a <hi>narrow Path,</hi> beſet here and there with Briars and Thorns; then, and not elſe, hath that man cauſe to complain of the unchearfulneſs of an Holy Life, who hath engaged to follow <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Leader, in the Duties and Contingencies of ſo Noble a Profeſſion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION VII.</head>
               <p>But I ſtill fear the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of all my Travails; not thinking any thing too Dear to be bought, or too Heavy to be borne, ſo I might be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>finiſh my Courſe with joy:</hi> I am told by my Saviour himſelf, <hi>that many ſhall ſeek to enter in at the ſtraight gate, and ſhall not be able to enter.</hi> If my former Sins be not pardoned, all I do will be to no purpoſe; the not accepting of my Perſon will render all the good I do contemptible, and puniſhable by God, as being ſo many <hi>guilded Sins,</hi> as ſuch moral Works are wont to be called.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115201:18"/>
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="12">12. IF nothing but your Pardon in your hand will ſatisfie you, and ſhake off the Scruples and Perplexities of your mind; you muſt know that this Pardon and Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ours, is rather under <hi>Promiſe</hi> now, and by <hi>Title</hi> of Law, then <hi>Actually</hi> pas'd upon our Souls in this Life: yet are not we the leſs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of it, for the Word of God is unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; but no man hath reaſon to expect, with <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconditionate</hi> and <hi>Abſolute</hi> Aſſurance, what muſt depend upon our own <hi>Co-operation</hi> with the Grace of God. And though God hath aſſured us, that <hi>He will not forſake us, till we forſake Him,</hi> no nor preſently then neither; yet what aſſurance we ſhall have of our own endeavours, muſt be ſought for in the promiſes of God made &amp; perform'd to his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Servants, and alſo in our own <hi>free Wills,</hi> and the preſeverance of them in Grace dayly and minutely begged of Him in Prayer.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 19.26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>ult.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6.</note> God firſt gives us grace to ask, then commands us to ask, then helps our Infirmities in asking, and promiſes he will give if we ask as he hath bid us; if then our wants be not ſupplyed, where will the fault lye but in our ſelves? Grace is cheaply enough obtained, if it may be had for the <hi>asking,</hi> and increas'd for the <hi>uſing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115201:19"/>
                  <p>But being you ſpeak of <hi>Gods not accepting your Perſon,</hi> as if that had ſo neceſſary and immediate an influence upon all your <hi>practice,</hi> that not only nothing were accepted without it, but every thing <hi>for</hi> it and <hi>from</hi> it; we will a little conſider that expreſsion, as it is uſed in Scripture, with reflection upon the <hi>erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> doctrine wherein you ſeem to me to be (I believe unwittingly) involved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To accept any ones perſon</hi> hath in Scripture a two-fold ſenſe: ſometimes it is taken in a good ſenſe, but not often, ſo in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.35. where <hi>David</hi> being interceeded with by the eloquence, wiſedom, and preſence of <hi>Abigail,</hi> changeth his determination of deſtroying her Husband <hi>Nabal</hi> and his Family, and this is there called <hi>an accepting of her Perſon.</hi> In a bad ſenſe it is more uſually found, ſo God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the <hi>Miniſters of Juſtice to accept Mens Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</hi> Lev. 16.15. and in this ſenſe it is, that God will not <hi>accept the Perſons of Men,</hi> 2 Sam. 14.14. Mat. 22.16. Gal. 2.6. yea in this ſenſe the <hi>Perſon of God Himſelf</hi> may be, but muſt not be <hi>accepted,</hi> as in <hi>Job.</hi> 13.7, 8. <hi>Will ye ſpeak wickedly for God, and talk deceitfully for him? will ye accept His perſon?</hi> wherein <hi>Job</hi> admoniſheth his Friends that they ſhould not argue for God (with opinion thereby to vindicate his Juſtice) from <hi>falſe Allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>Jobs Hypocriſy.</hi> So do thoſe men, who <hi>equivocate,</hi> or <hi>lye, ſteal, rob,</hi> commit <hi>Sacriledge</hi> and <hi>murder for Gods glory, &amp;c. accept the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115201:19"/>
                  <p>When therefore the Phraſe of <hi>[accepting of mens perſons]</hi> is uſed in a good ſenſe, it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies thus much, that the perſon of ſuch a man in <hi>conjunction with his good qualifications,</hi> or deſerts, is accepted &amp; rewarded: but when it ſignifies to a bad ſenſe, then it imports thus much; that ſuch a Man is accepted, favour'd, or rewarded, without any <hi>intuition</hi> of his <hi>Qualifications</hi> be they good or evil; this is Partiality and Injuſtice, and we may not uſe it even for God himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Now by your Objection, I conceive, you believe that he is an Accepter of Perſons in this laſt ſenſe, viz. an <hi>abſolute Elector,</hi> who out of the <hi>maſs</hi> of Mankind corrupted, did by vertue of his <hi>Soveraign power,</hi> and <hi>Omnipotent will, irreſpectively</hi> chooſe ſome few mens <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and reprobate Myriades of others, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>previſional regard</hi> to their Works, expreſly contrary to that of Saint <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 2.6. where the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects no Mans perſon,</hi> (the Gentiles being as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible in Gods eye, as <hi>the lineal ſeed of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> of which the <hi>Jews</hi> could not eaſily be perſwaded;) neither <hi>Iames</hi> nor <hi>Peter</hi> who ſeemed to be <hi>Pillars,</hi> being preferred and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected before Saint <hi>Paul, (a late abortive Convert,)</hi> by <hi>Him who ſeeth not as Man ſeeth.</hi> And therefore if God hath not elected ſome, and reprobated others, without <hi>previſion</hi> and <hi>Intuition</hi> of their Qualifications; as fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing what good, or what bad, or what no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115201:20"/>men would make of <hi>Grace given,</hi> and conſequently, thereby <hi>aſſure</hi> or <hi>diveſt</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the Advantages and Priviledges of <hi>Gods common Love to Mankinde;</hi> your fear of not being accepted, becauſe God hath from all Eternity ſome <hi>Quarrel</hi> or <hi>No Love</hi> to your Perſon, is not only frivolous, but dangerous, and in it ſelf <hi>deſtructive</hi> of all your Labours and Endeavours for eternal Life; <hi>keeping</hi> them under the <hi>diſmal,</hi> and falſe Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Tyranny</hi> in the Divine Majeſty, which the Heathens themſelves rejected, under the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To be ſhort, I ſhall only confront the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of God to <hi>Cain, Gen.</hi> 4.7. (whom I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi>Aſſertors</hi> of that Doctrine have ever held to be a Reprobate) againſt the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Argument that may be uſed for inducing and confirming the belief of this <hi>proſopolepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> way of electing and reprobating men, without any intuition of their good or evil deeds: <hi>[If thou do well, ſhall thou not be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?]</hi> from whence are inferred theſe two things; Firſt, that <hi>Cain</hi> himſelf might have offered an acceptable Sacrifice to God as well as <hi>Abel;</hi> and <hi>Secondly,</hi> if he had done ſo, he had been accepted by God, as well as was his brother. So that it was not any Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and Hatred that God had to the <hi>Perſon</hi> of <hi>Cain irreſpectively</hi> conſidered; but either to the evil that he had <hi>formerly done</hi> (for we cannot preſume <hi>Cain</hi> to have lived without
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115201:20"/>ſin, till the time of the offering that Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, nor doth the Text aſſert, <hi>that</hi> to be the <hi>firſt</hi> Sacrifice, that either he, or <hi>Abel</hi> offered) or that which he had now committed in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> not worthy Gods accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at his hands.</p>
                  <p>What reaſon therefore you ſhould have to fear the ſucceſs of your Labours in the Lord, upon <hi>Miſpriſion</hi> of <hi>Perſonal Acceptance</hi> with God, you ſee by what hath been ſaid; as alſo of your <hi>groundleſs</hi> fears of not being <hi>able to enter in at the ſtraight Gate;</hi> our Saviour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (if you mark it) threatned, not them who <hi>ſtrive</hi> (becauſe he hath commanded that <hi>active, induſtrious</hi> way of attempting) but them who only <hi>ſeek,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> (a way of getting Heaven very different from the former) importing very little more (though no more to the purpoſe) than <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> Wiſh, that he <hi>might dye the death of the righteous. Numb.</hi> 23.10.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION VIII.</head>
               <p>But though it will follow from hence that <hi>Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Aſſurance of Remiſſion and Pardon of Sin, be not alwayes a neceſſary effect of Gods pardoning of us, or our being in a <hi>way</hi> to be pardoned: yet ſurely it is ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115201:21"/>(ſay you) that the clean contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> a perſwaſion that I ſhall not be pardoned, ſhould flow from ſo happy a condition, as you would make me believe I am In.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="13">13. IF you ſhould throughly examine your ſelf; that you do thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your ſelf, will undoubtedly appear to be falſe. For to what purpoſe do you then <hi>pray, faſt,</hi> and <hi>give alms,</hi> lead a <hi>ſtrict</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere</hi> life, &amp;c. if you were indeed perſwaded that you ſhall not be ſaved? would any one but a mad man keep on his pace, in rough, and almoſt impaſſable wayes, if he were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly aſſured, that he ſhould never come to his journeys end? his feet muſt needs be thought to confute his tongue, if he ſhould do thus.</p>
                  <p>Beſides how prepoſterous a thing were it, if you ſhould take ſuch <hi>ſharp</hi> and <hi>ſevere</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as you do, to enlarge your ſcore, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing all theſe Actions of yours ſhould be charged by God upon your account, as ſo many <hi>guilded</hi> ſins, as you lately termed them? But this, I think, you will have little reaſon to be afraid of, ſeeing our Saviour hath told you, that the Alms-deeds and Prayers of the Phariſees themſelves were ſo rewarded, as they deſired they ſhould be, (<hi>viz.</hi> with the <hi>Praiſes</hi> and <hi>Commendation</hi> of men, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.16)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115201:21"/>and are not by him either ſtil'd ſins, or threatned with any puniſhment, more then with the no-ground of expecting a Reward from God.</p>
                  <p>But as concerning the pardon of our ſin, it will be very uſeful to obſerve theſe four things. 1. That the point of Faith, concerning <hi>Remiſſion of Sin,</hi> is, That by <hi>Chriſt, Remiſſion of Sins</hi> is given to Mankinde through Faith in his Blood. 2. That this <hi>Remiſſion</hi> is not <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely,</hi> though <hi>freely</hi> given; but doth depend upon certain <hi>Conditions</hi> or Qualifications, whereby men are made fit and capable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it. 3. That the Rules as well for the means of conveying this <hi>Donation</hi> to us, as for our aptitude and capacity to receive the benefit thereof, are to be ſought out and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Scriptures. 4. That becauſe many things of Importance, concerning this doctrine, are to be deduced from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, by the <hi>Mediation</hi> of humane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it is a mark both of Piety, Wiſdom, and Humility, to take the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> for our Guide, and relyance therein. Falſe Interpretations of Scripture, prove either full of Perplexity, or Danger, or both, to our ſelves and others; but moſt eſpecially in ſuch Doctrines, ſo nearly importing our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as this of <hi>Remiſſion of Sin</hi> doth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not to be regarded, by what <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums,</hi> or from what <hi>Principles</hi> your concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are drawn, if they be only your <hi>own:</hi> if
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115201:22"/>you mean to ſayl ſecurely amidſt the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts raiſed in the World by ſuch diverſity of Judgements and Imaginations, embarque your ſelf in the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Conſentient,</hi> and <hi>Ancient Interpretations</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> and do not adventure ſo pretious a Fraught, as is your ſoul, redeemed with the bloud of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the <hi>tottering Boat</hi> of your own, or other mens <hi>private Interpretations</hi> of Scripture. The <hi>Church</hi> teacheth you this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That you are pardonable upon your Faith and Repentance. 2. That God hath promiſed (who cannot lye, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18.) that he will pardon you, if you believe and and repent. 3. That the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of Gods pardoning your ſins, is at preſent but imperfectly, and inchoately wrought in your Heart by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the uſe of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but the full Evidence thereof is to be expected from <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Judge, and to be patiently, and chearfully waited for by Faith in the promiſes. 4. That the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of your own <hi>Spirit,</hi> ariſing from your ſincere converſation in the doctrines of the Goſpel, is the moſt <hi>certain Evidence,</hi> that you or any man can <hi>ordinarily</hi> expect in this life: and all this from pregnant Teſtimony of Scripture.</p>
                  <p>For you, who hold a lawful and uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Succeſſion of <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſth, you cannot but believe, that in the hands of the Church lyes much of your Peace, as well as of your ſafety: conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115201:22"/>the <hi>Power</hi> they have <hi>over</hi> you, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. and the <hi>Power</hi> they have <hi>for</hi> you, <hi>John</hi> 20.21.22.23. and <hi>both</hi> theſe derived down to this preſent Age, and ſhall ſo continue whereſoever the Church ſhall be, (though there be no neceſſity that they ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued whereſoever Chriſtians are) by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of our Saviours promiſe, even to the end of the World. And theſe <hi>powers</hi> to be pleaded for <hi>by them,</hi> and ſubmitted unto <hi>by you,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Divine right;</hi> framed and appointed by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> (the principal <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator</hi> of <hi>Church-Government</hi>) for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and Edification of the <hi>Bodie of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I doubt there be ſome, and thoſe no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable ones, that believe this doctrine not <hi>ſufficiently</hi> aſſerted by the <hi>Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> there being in the Frame and Contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of her <hi>Church-Government,</hi> too much of the <hi>Lay,</hi> and too little of the <hi>Clergy-man.</hi> And though my Judgement tells me, that there is not any <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> on earth, be he <hi>Emperour, King</hi> or <hi>Prince,</hi> that hath ſo <hi>Evident,</hi> and <hi>Immediate</hi> a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> for his <hi>Power,</hi> and the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> thereof, as hath the <hi>Church:</hi> yet who ſees not, that both the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, and the Adminiſtrators of this Government are <hi>deſpiſed,</hi> ſave in ſuch a <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate way</hi> of diſpenſing this <hi>power,</hi> that muſt needs render it <hi>precarious</hi> in the eyes of ignorant men, and the <hi>Church Officers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115201:23"/>no other things, but ſuch <hi>borrowed Hands,</hi> as by <hi>pulling,</hi> now this <hi>way,</hi> now that <hi>way,</hi> help to keep the <hi>carriage</hi> of the <hi>Civil State</hi> from <hi>overturning</hi> in <hi>rough</hi> and <hi>dangerous Deſcents</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION IX.</head>
               <p>But you ſay, that could you have believed the point of <hi>Sacerdotal Abſolution,</hi> and the Obligation (<hi>that</hi> ſeems to inferre) to <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Confeſſion;</hi> you had long ſince en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed your Peace, at leaſt you had not felt ſo great a trouble as now you do.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="14">14. OUr Judgements no whit differ in this, for I clearly believe, that on earth, as there is no ſurer way to prevent mens falling into ſin (eſpecially many <hi>cloſe</hi> Enormities) then the <hi>diſcreet</hi> and <hi>conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practiſe</hi> of the Duty of <hi>Confeſſion:</hi> ſo is there not a more proper and undoubted way, for allaying the Troubles of minde, flowing from the guilt of Sin; then a <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate Execution,</hi> of the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Abſolving Sinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſay the <hi>power of abſolving Sinners;</hi> for if this Clauſe in his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> ſtand not good
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115201:23"/>by <hi>Divine Right;</hi> I know nothing a <hi>Prieſt</hi> can do more then other men; and am well aſſured, that in ſome part of their Office, they can do (many of them) much leſs. Not to ſignifie any thing of the grief I have, for your not believing ſo evident Texts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as this Doctrine is built upon; I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to cut up your Infidelity in this point by the Roots, by a very brief Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of theſe few particulars. 1. What the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Abſolving</hi> is. 2 Whether it be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed</hi> down to the <hi>preſent Paſtors</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> in the ordinary way of commiſſioning them to that Function, by the <hi>Impoſition</hi> of the hands of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Preſbyters.</hi> 3. Of what <hi>concernment</hi> this Power is, in the Execution thereof, upon Penitent Sinners.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Abſolving</hi> Sinners, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in one branch of the <hi>power of the Keyes, viz.</hi> remitting ſin: expreſsly mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chriſts Commiſſion given to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and their Succeſſors, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23. which in the point in hand, as it much differs from <hi>re-admitting</hi> into the Church, (that part of the <hi>power of the Keyes</hi> which ſeems, and doth but ſeem to be the ſame with this) ſo is it in a <hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>Presbyter</hi> (to my Judgment) no <hi>judicial,</hi> but rather an <hi>Annuntiative</hi> act, the Prieſt being none of that order to whom the promiſe of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is made, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.28. <hi>of ſitting on twelve thrones, and judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael.</hi> My reaſon for my opinion is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115201:24"/>a <hi>Prieſt</hi> cannot be thought to <hi>Abſolve</hi> otherwiſe, then he can <hi>Retein</hi> (elſe there will be <hi>more</hi> in one, then in the other of the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relatives,</hi>) Now a <hi>Prieſt</hi> doth not <hi>retein</hi> ſin <hi>judicially</hi> (for that is the office of the Biſhop, and is onely done by the ſentence of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi>) but <hi>declaratively</hi> only, ſhewing the Impenitents (whether collectively, or perſonally) that by reaſon of ſuch or ſuch Impediments, their ſins are not forgiven; but not <hi>binding</hi> their ſins upon them <hi>judicially,</hi> ſo that the Offender ſhall not only be obliged to repent, but alſo (as under the ſentence of <hi>Excommunication</hi>) to <hi>ſue</hi> for the removal of the Cenſure. Like as in the <hi>Law,</hi> one who is ſued to an <hi>Outlawry</hi> for Debt, muſt as well procure the <hi>Writ</hi> of <hi>Outlawry</hi> againſt him to be <hi>reverſt,</hi> as take care to pay the Debt.</p>
                  <p>Neither do I by this, make the <hi>pronouncing</hi> of a ſinner abſolved, by a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> to be of no more efficacy then if a <hi>Layman</hi> had done it: for a power to <hi>pronounce</hi> or <hi>proclaim</hi> a Pardon in the name of a Prince, by vertue of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion iſſued out to one for that purpoſe, or by one to whoſe <hi>office</hi> it belongs ſo to do; is quite another thing, then the ſame Pardon <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported</hi> by one, who hath no power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to proclaim the Princes pardon.</p>
                  <p>But if I am thought by this to infringe the power and priviledge of the <hi>Sacerdotal</hi> Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and any way to leſſen the Authority of that <hi>Order;</hi> I muſt ſpeak my minde freely,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115201:24"/>I do not conceive that the ſame words in the <hi>Ordination</hi> of a Prieſt, do in the <hi>Intention</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> ſignify to the ſame latitude, as they did in the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I believe a <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> doth no (more, but yet as much) in this point, as the <hi>Church</hi> hath inveſted him with in her Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him to that Function; which is the exerciſe of an Authority <hi>limited,</hi> as I have already ſaid.</p>
                  <p>However this is enough for the Penitent, for if the Prieſt hath Judgment (which in Reverence to the <hi>Church</hi> which hath had In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of his abilities we ought to believe) to diſcern when the Penitent is pardonable, you cannot deny but he hath authority com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him, in Gods Name, and from his Word, to let the Penitent know, not only that he is pardonable, but that God will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly pardon him, and all ſuch as he is; in caſe of their Perſeverance in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As for the ſecond thing propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> whether this <hi>power</hi> be ſo <hi>conveyed</hi> down, &amp;c. it is ſtrange, me thinks, it ſhould be any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſcruple to you. For if you had not ſome prejudice to every thing that <hi>relates</hi> to pardon of Sin, I would ask you (and do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſuppoſe ſhould go away without an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer) whether you believe a <hi>Presbyter</hi> hath power to <hi>conſecrate</hi> the Elements in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament, by vertue of this Ordination?
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115201:25"/>and whether a <hi>Lay-man</hi> can do as much therein, if he ſhould take the <hi>Common prayer Book,</hi> and read over the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> the <hi>Form</hi> of the <hi>Conſecration?</hi> I know you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the later as much as you believe the former. What hinders then, that this <hi>branch</hi> of power ſhould not be conferred upon him in his <hi>Ordination?</hi> The Authority conferred upon the <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the ſame in both, and both are by the Church (with due Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) inveſted on the Presbyter in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination. And good reaſon it ſhould be ſo, for I doubt not that the Sacrament ought <hi>(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly)</hi> to be adminiſtred to none but <hi>abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> perſons; as none were to eat the Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, but thoſe who were clean from all <hi>Legal</hi> pollutions. We ſee that the Presbyterians, and all other Sectaries amongſt us, are ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this point, that they are ſo far from leſſening the Authority of their Church-offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in this particular, (or at leaſt of the whole Church as they pleaſe to terme it) that they are much more rigid and ſevere, in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Power like this, <hi>of their own making,</hi> then ever the Biſhops were, in putting the <hi>power Chriſt undoubtedly gave them,</hi> in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But I need not ſay much of this ſecond <hi>branch</hi> to one of your <hi>perſwaſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Laſtly, if you deſire to know what <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,</hi> this is to a Penitent? I anſwer, that if a Penitent do but believe, as much of the Prieſts authority (though I ſhall be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115201:25"/>thought no very great friend to the inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it) as I have aſſerted; viz. an <hi>Annnncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power</hi> from God not only to <hi>declare</hi> men <hi>Pardonable</hi> (as he doth in preaching the Goſpel) but to <hi>pronounce</hi> them <hi>pardoned,</hi> upon inſpection of their faith and repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as he doth in giving them <hi>abſolution;</hi> he ſhall not only recieve comfort, by the Preiſts aſſuring him of the ſafety of his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of his <hi>redintegration</hi> into grace and favour with God; but ſhall enjoy the benefit of <hi>his</hi> prayers, whom God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to that Duty moſt eſpecially, and whom he hath promiſed to accept: toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> of the Prieſt (<hi>Bleſſing</hi> him in Gods ſtead as well as in Gods name) a favour which nothing but ſome lend <hi>Hoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni's,</hi> and <hi>Phinees</hi>'s amongſt the <hi>Clergie. Numb.</hi> 6.23.27. but multitudes of prophane <hi>Eſau's</hi> amongſt the <hi>Layety,</hi> could have had the skill or luck to have rendered ſo contemptible as we ſee it is, the puniſhment whereof (as likewiſe of <hi>Deſpiſing</hi> the Perſons and Offices of ſuch whom God hath appointed to ſerve at the <hi>Altar of Bleſſing,</hi> in many other particulars) both this preſent and many future unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Ages ſhall (as well as have ſome paſs't times) undoubtedly bear, even to the <hi>removall</hi> of the <hi>Golden Candelſtick</hi> from among them.</p>
                  <p>That thus a Prieſt is inabled to do, is cleare from the <hi>Form of Abſolution,</hi> appointed in the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115201:26"/>
                     <hi>Liturgie</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> to be uſed in the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of the ſick,</hi> wherein as the Authority of the Church in that point, as alſo of the Prieſt, are plainly aſſerted, ſo is it matter of wonder, that ſo many <hi>Legall</hi> Proteſtants have ſuch a ſlender reſpect for an important and neceſſarie duty, it is not to be believed that either that <hi>Power</hi> of the Prieſt that <hi>form of abſolution,</hi> and the <hi>Duty of Confeſſion</hi> are reſerved to be huddled up in ſo troubleſome an hour, and all the time of health paſt over without any inquiry into our <hi>Accounts:</hi> the Church injoyns it to be uſed then, but doth not forbid the uſe of it at other times. My advice to you is that if you deſire the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie of your own Peace of conſcience; you put this Duty in practiſe more frequently, and ſee that your Ghoſtly Father, do his Duty in this and no other <hi>forme of Abſolution,</hi> (I mean any of his own making) leaſt by ſome <hi>error</hi> he may <hi>ſeem</hi> to do more then his power will permit him, or not do as much as the Church hath enjoyned.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION X.</head>
               <p>You will ſay perhaps what ſettlement of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by a <hi>Sacerdotal Abſolution?</hi> ſeeing the Prieſt can but ſee, with the eyes of a Man, and hath no Knowledge of my heart;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115201:26"/>which is ſo <hi>Deceitful,</hi> that it is a very great difficulty, for any man to finde it out, though it lodg in his own breaſt, and if he had knowledge thereof, yet is the Act but <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,</hi> not <hi>Diſpoticall,</hi> and who knows whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God will <hi>confirme</hi> it or no.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="15">15. THe Prieſt <hi>ſeeth but as man ſeeth,</hi> but he may ſee what you ſee not, and judge better of what he ſees then every common perſon, ſeeing <hi>the lips of the Prieſt do preſerve knowledge.</hi> If therefore he have underſtanding to diſcerne and judge aright of what he ſees, (as you muſt ſuppoſe he hath, elſe you will (at leaſt) condemn your ſelf of an unreaſonable choyce) it is your buiſineſs, to lay your Soul before him; and to acquaint him throughly, and truly, with your Condition: if you fail in this (and conſequently the <hi>Act</hi> be done under an error) the blame hereof will light on none but your ſelf. And as for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of your wayes, there is no doubt but if St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Rule be true, though nothing elſe without us but God doth, yet the <hi>Spirit of a man doth know the things of a man,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. and the heart may be <hi>Emptied</hi> to the very bottom, by ſuch rules as a judicious prudent and pious <hi>Confeſſor</hi> ſhall preſcribe.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115201:27"/>
                  <p>But in the later part of your Objection, I am ſorry to hear any queſtion made of Gods <hi>confirmation</hi> of that due and neceſſarie <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Abſolution</hi> made in His name, and by vertue of a Commiſſion derived from him. Any thing of this nature amongſt men, would ſound too infamous, eſpecially if fixt upon ſuch Perſons who have the Power and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Giving commiſſions</hi> to other men. To queſtion Gods faithfulneſs, is a ſin of infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and he that hath promiſed under the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond covenant, <hi>he will remember our Sins and Iniquities no more,</hi> Heb. 8.12. <hi>i. e.</hi> of ſuch as embrace the Goſpel preach'd unto them.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. To conclude my Anſwer fully to theſe <hi>two</hi> laſt Objections, I ſuppoſe, that becauſe we have no <hi>viſible bloody Sacrifice,</hi> nor a <hi>Moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy</hi> (on Earth) into which the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> may enter with <hi>blood</hi> for his <hi>own</hi> and <hi>our</hi> Sins, it is therefore a matter of difficulty in your judgement to be aſcertained of the <hi>way</hi> of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining pardon for Sinners under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; the means of doing it being ſo ſecret and inviſible, and the Threatnings (in caſe it be not done) ſo open and terrible.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle tells us plainly, That <hi>Ieſus Chriſt is the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever: Heb.</hi> 13.8. which imports not only the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutability</hi> of Gods accepting <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>meritorious</hi> cauſe of Remiſſion of Sins, but alſo the <hi>unchangeableneſs</hi> of that <hi>method,</hi> whereby this Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the Goſper is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115201:27"/>adminiſtred. For this later, which moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns your caſe, the Apoſtle tells you, <hi>that Chriſt ever liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th to make interceſſion for us,</hi> Heb. 7.25. this being the moſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of his Office in the adminiſtration of his <hi>mediatory</hi> Kingdom. This <hi>Iaterceſſion</hi> for us, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Church in general, and each one in particular, being his own <hi>immediate Act</hi> in Heaven, (and prefigured unto us by the High-prieſts going into the <hi>Moſt-holy,</hi> once only in every year, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.8.) doth conſiſt of <hi>two</hi> branches, becauſe it ſuppoſeth that we have need of <hi>two</hi> things, <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification,</hi> therefore doth our <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> intercede with his Father for <hi>two</hi> things; for 1. <hi>pardon of Sin,</hi> for 2. <hi>grace of Obedience,</hi> or holy living; and theſe not <hi>intermitted,</hi> but <hi>continued</hi> Acts of interceſſion for <hi>us,</hi> to the end of our lives, and for <hi>all</hi> unto the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>And this <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Interceſſion</hi> for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is two fold; Firſt a <hi>preventive act</hi> of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, (or rather the <hi>beginning</hi> of an <hi>Act</hi> continued to <hi>higher degrees</hi>) whereby Chriſt doth <hi>intercede</hi> with God for us, that the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal forfeiture</hi> of our lives by ſin, may not be taken immediately after the Fact; and alſo that <hi>Grace of Repentance</hi> may be given us: of this nature I conceive that <hi>Interceſſional</hi> prayer of our Saviour, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.34. <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do.</hi> Where though the giving to ſuch men Repentance
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115201:28"/>be not expreſt, yet is it (queſtionleſs) imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe without Repentance they cannot be pardoned. The <hi>ſecond branch</hi> of this <hi>Act</hi> is a <hi>ſubſequent mediatorie act</hi> of prayer, or <hi>[Plea]</hi> with God (for ſo much the word <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi> will bear, <hi>(if any man ſin, we have an Advocate, &amp;c.)</hi> on the behalf of the ſinner repenting; whereby Pardon is procured for him, upon Gods <hi>Foreſight,</hi> that his Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Repentance will be ſincerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, by the vertue and efficacy of the grace of perſeverance, which is interceded for by Chriſt, and obteined, upon the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents <hi>uſing</hi> the <hi>former</hi> meaſure of <hi>aſſiſting</hi> grace; and this, as a bleſſing upon, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his ſincere endeavours of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p>This later <hi>branch</hi> of <hi>Chriſts interceſſion</hi> for pardon, is that, whereby Chriſt the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor doth receive into his protection, the <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liating acts</hi> of a penitent ſoul, <hi>perfuming</hi> the Tears and prayers of ſuch a one, with <hi>clouds</hi> of his own moſt precious <hi>Incenſe;</hi> and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his <hi>own,</hi> offering them to Allmigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, as the fruits of his <hi>former Mediation,</hi> and an earneſt of that enlargement of his Church, which, as it is the <hi>travail of his ſoul, Iai.</hi> 53.11. which he delights to ſee, ſo will it be the <hi>joy of the holy Angels in the preſence of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">16. Upon this <hi>Interceſſion</hi> of Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends our pardon of Sin, and renovation by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115201:28"/>Grace: from <hi>hence</hi> it is, that all but <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> and ſuch as ceaſe not to <hi>do deſpight to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God,</hi> by a continued preſumptuous and malitious courſe of Sinning, receive a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit apportionate to their ſeveral <hi>Stations</hi> and <hi>Degrees.</hi> And that you have no reaſon to think your ſelf <hi>rejected,</hi> into the <hi>fatal portion</hi> of them, (being indeed the purchaſe of the ſinner himſelf, thus cruel to his own ſoul) who have no advantage, (nay not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all) by this <hi>Interceſſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> your Eyes fill'd with your Tears, and your Ears deafned with your own Sighs, your Hands ſo buſy in diſtributing Alms, your Feet ſo Active in viſiting the Sick, and your Knees made <hi>callous</hi> (like the Primitive Saints) with frequent <hi>Prayings,</hi> are a ſufficient witneſs to your ſelf, and to all the world beſide.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECT. XIII.</head>
               <p>But you Reply. Did not <hi>Eſau ſeek the Bleſſing with Tears,</hi> and yet miſs'd of it.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="17">17. BUt I preſume you think St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath put this Objection into your mouth; but if you pleaſe to ſurvey the place in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.16, 17. you ſhall finde that this
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115201:29"/>doth not reach you, unleſs you have at any time <hi>ſold</hi> the <hi>bleſſing</hi> for a <hi>meſs of pottage,</hi> i. e. <hi>renounc't</hi> your intereſt in the land of Promiſe, (the pretious promiſes of the Goſpel,) for the enjoyment of that Plenty, Honour, peace, &amp;c. <hi>the Pomps and vanities of this wicked World;</hi> I ſay <hi>renounc't</hi> your part and intereſt in the Merits and Mediation of Chriſt; and that not <hi>indirectly</hi> and <hi>remotely</hi> (as all who are guilty of <hi>wilful ſins</hi> in ſome meaſure do) but <hi>orally, ſcandalouſly</hi> and <hi>treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly;</hi> which (I preſume) you will not forge, and charge upon your ſelf; though your fancy hath a large <hi>Shop,</hi> and many <hi>Tools</hi> to work with.</p>
                  <p>Seeing then, that by vertue of that <hi>preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional act</hi> of <hi>interceſſion,</hi> (lately mentioned) you have not been cut off in your ſins; but have <hi>your life given unto you for a prey;</hi> and withal, Grace for Repentance unto life, which like good <hi>Phyſick,</hi> by reaſon of a <hi>maſs</hi> of <hi>crude</hi> humors in the Stomack) doth thus work ſomewhat violently in your ſoul; why ſhould you doubt that other <hi>ſubſequent Act</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Interceſſion,</hi> whereby your pardon will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained? hath <hi>God pleaſure in the death of him that dyeth?</hi> doth not he ſwear he hath not? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. and hath the <hi>Divine Majeſty</hi> ſo far loſt his credit with you, as not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iveled upon his oath? can he which is <hi>Love</hi> it <hi>ſelf,</hi> not only ſcorn, but hate the Proſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Sinner? that Sinner, whoſe eyes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115201:29"/>would be content to pour out Rivers of bloud before the throne of Grace, to obtain a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with the offended Majeſtie of Heaven? even that Reconciliation which Himſelf <hi>prayes from us men,</hi> by the <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> of his Holy Goſpel, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath told us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. O do not thus ſtruggle to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive your ſelf of your intereſt, and ſhare in thoſe merciful imbraces, which haſten to <hi>meet,</hi> and not fly from <hi>Repenting</hi> Sinners!</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECT. XIV.</head>
               <p>But yet ſtill, me thinketh, my Sins are ſuch, as God cannot in Juſtice paſs by; his promiſes are too pretious to belong to me; more <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate</hi> Sinners, and ſuch who have not ſo violenced the Law of God, and provok't his Long-fuffering, may (doubtleſs) have the benefit of them: but as for me, why ſhould not my Lot be with them, who but <hi>for ten times provoking</hi> were for ever ſecluded the Land of Promiſe.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="18">18. YOur Charity is very commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that can make you believe ſo much for others, and ſo little for your ſelf: but you ſhould do well to remember, that the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115201:30"/>
                     <hi>Attributes of the Divine Majeſty,</hi> may not be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by us; not that I think any one ſo fooliſh, as to attempt it in reſpect of their <hi>nature,</hi> which is impoſſible; but in reſpect of their <hi>effects</hi> which to do is ſinfull, they are infinite in their own nature, and muſt be ſo in our eſteem: to ſay God cannot forgive your ſins, is a ſin againſt his power and juſtice; to ſay he will not (where he hath promiſed) is a ſin againſt his truth and goodneſſe. His goodneſs hath made him promiſe that he will do it; and that he might make this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe good, he hath provided a full <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to his <hi>juſtice,</hi> and all this as much <hi>before</hi> us, as <hi>without</hi> us, and this limited as fully and as largely to you, as to any other Chriſtian in the world.</p>
                  <p>This you cannot but ſee, in that moſt comfortable and full affirmation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. Heb. 2.9. When he tells you plainly that it was the deſign of Gods Grace. <hi>That Chriſt ſhould taſt death for every man:</hi> and <hi>God ſo loved the World</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>John. cap.</hi> 3.16.) <hi>That he gave his only begotten ſon, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for that example of Gods wrath upon the <hi>Provoakers,</hi> (which you think doth ſo <hi>neerly</hi> concerne you, becauſe you have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned willfully more then ten times;) you muſt give me leave to tell you, that you are very unfortunate in your application of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115201:30"/>Scripture; this example not <hi>reaching home</hi> to your caſe, indeed <hi>over-reaching</hi> it more then <hi>Jonathans</hi> third arrow did the Lad that fetcht the other two. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. For the <hi>Caution</hi> given by the Apoſtle to the Hebrews, in that place is, that they take care of <hi>falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> from the Goſpell, upon temptations or perſecutions; and ſo after the example of many already fallen from the faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould become Apoſtates; whereby they might be ſure that the promiſes of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſhould be no matter of advantage to them, becauſe they ſhould be as certain <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> to enter in Gods reſt; as were thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voakers in the Wilderneſſe, who for temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God ſo often, were <hi>finally</hi> by Gods <hi>Oath</hi> excluded, from all hopes of entring into the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> their Carkeſſes falling in the Wilderneſſe, as the <hi>trophees</hi> of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon them, for their infidelity of his power, and goodneſſe, and promiſe.</p>
                  <p>This (I doubt not) doth clearly appear unto you (unleſſe you have engaged never to <hi>repudiate</hi> your <hi>pregnant</hi> fancy, how <hi>Spurious</hi> ſoever her conceptions are) to be of no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to your caſe: who carry in your breaſt, ſo many <hi>witneſſes</hi> of your belief of the Goſpell, eſpecially the <hi>threatning</hi> part of it, that (as your poſture is for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) to fear your Apoſtacy from the faith of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> were an apprehenſion <hi>too remote</hi> from all excuſes allowable even to perſons of your <hi>temper.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="objection">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115201:31"/>
               <head>OBJECTION</head>
               <p>Yet who knows but I may <hi>fall away?</hi> I am not yet perſwaded that I ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="19">19. THough my prayer to God for you is that you may not be ſo perſwaded <hi>totally,</hi> and <hi>finally,</hi> yet if any one ſhould be ſo, it doth not therefore follow, that ſuch a one is <hi>fallen</hi> from the faith of the Goſpel: for the belief of this is ſo far from being a disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that it is not ſo much a <hi>direct disbleif</hi> of any part of the word of God; becauſe God hath no where declared by <hi>ſpeciall affirmation,</hi> that ſuch a man ſhall be ſaved. But be it that you were perſwaded that you ſhould be ſaved, neither of theſe <hi>two</hi> things would follow thereupon, either <hi>firſt,</hi> therefore I ſhall infallibly be ſaved, or 2. I am aſſured that I ſhall never be an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> becauſe I <hi>thus</hi> believe, for what text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth affirme this propoſition, viz. he that is firmly perſwaded that he ſhall be ſaved, ſhall <hi>never</hi> become an <hi>Apoſtate?</hi> or this, he that believeth he ſhall be ſaved, ſhall <hi>infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> be ſaved?</p>
                  <p>In a word, had you an <hi>Aſſurance</hi> of your ſalvation <hi>abſolutely,</hi> and <hi>unconditionately</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto you, by all the <hi>Divines</hi> in the world; yet was this but an <hi>humane aſſurance,</hi> and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115201:31"/>could amount to no more, but a teſtimony from men, the ſtability whereof would be as demonſtrable as their own mortality, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>evidence</hi> of this Propoſition [you ſhall infallibly be ſaved] is taken from the <hi>will of Gods purpoſe</hi> concerning that man, to which <hi>ſecret will,</hi> of the <hi>Divine Majeſtie,</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that concern <hi>Gods preſcience</hi> do belong, though indeed the <hi>conditionall aſſur ance</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans ſalvation, doth relate to his <hi>reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed will.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION. XIV.</head>
               <p>But doth not <hi>St.</hi> Paul. tell us Rom. <hi>8.16. That the Spirit it ſelf beareth witneſs with our Spirit that we are the Children of God?</hi> I want <hi>both</hi> theſe teſtimonies of my Adoption, that of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of adoption and that of mine owne <hi>Spirit</hi> witneſſing that I am a Child of God: ſurely then my condition is not ſuch as it ought to be, and as I deſire it ſhould be.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="20">20. THat this Epiſtle of S. <hi>Paul</hi> (and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. and 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Chapters) hath in it ſome things that <hi>are hard to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood,</hi> thoſe <hi>Eſau,</hi> and <hi>Jacob-like</hi> conteſts in the <hi>Bowels</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> about the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115201:32"/>thereof, do ſufficiently witneſſe: I pray God that we may all of us, in the heat and animoſity of our diſputes, have an eye to that example of <hi>admonition St. Peter</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe in his times who being <hi>unlearned</hi> and <hi>unſtable, did wreſt thoſe and other Scriptures to their own deſtruction.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>I am perſasaded better things of you, and ſuch as accompany ſalvation.</hi> And therefore to give you a full and <hi>tender</hi> account of your objection, I conceive it conſiſts of 3. branches. 1. You ſuppoſe that every Child of God hath <hi>teſtimony</hi> that he is ſuch. 2. that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſſerts the <hi>teſtimony</hi> to be <hi>twofold</hi> one the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Spirit of adoption,</hi> the other the <hi>teſtimony of his own Spirit.</hi> and 3. that you <hi>want</hi> both theſe and therefore <hi>haſtily</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that you are not the child of God. To theſe I ſhall anſwer diſtinctly thus.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I do affirm with your ſuppoſition that every child of God, hath <hi>teſtimony,</hi> or <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> that he is ſuch. I ſhall give you but one place for all, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Whoſoeuer is born of God doth not commit ſin i. e. he is ſuch a one as keeps a ſincere Eye upon himſelf in reſpect of all, eſpecially of deliberate ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. I am likewiſe of your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that this <hi>teſtimony</hi> is the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Spirit of adoption,</hi> and of his own <hi>Spirit;</hi> but whether it be neceſſary that a child of God have <hi>both</hi> theſe <hi>teſtimonies,</hi> giving the like full and <hi>joynt evidence</hi> for his ſonſhip; and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115201:32"/>therefore till ſuch <hi>full</hi> and <hi>joynt-evidence</hi> be given to him, he <hi>really</hi> is not (and therefore ought not to repute himſelf) a child of God is more then matter of doubt with you hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (it ſeems) indiſſolvably eſpouſed the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative part. But <hi>I</hi> doubt you do not rightly apprehend what the Apoſtle doth mean by <hi>[the ſelf ſame, or the Spirit it ſelf bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs]</hi> with our Spirrit, to me he ſeems to mean one or rather all of theſe 3. things, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 1. The Witneſs of Scripture (which in the <hi>teſtimonie</hi> of the Spirit of God) that ſuch as believe in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, i. e.</hi> receive him as their Prieſt Prophet and King, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly adopted into God <hi>paternall Relation to Christ Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>adoption by Grace, as</hi> truely intereſſing thoſe believers in Gods Paternity, as doth the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> Chriſt himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of St. <hi>John. cap.</hi> 1.12. <hi>As many as received him, to them gave he power to become the ſons of God, even to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on his name.</hi> and this <hi>teſtimony</hi> have all the ſons of God, or all true believers. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly it may ſignifie the <hi>aeconomy</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in oppoſition to that of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> whoſe ſtate or condition, was that of Servitude; as ours under the Goſpel is a ſtate of Freedom they Servants, we Sons: they full of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of bondage, engendered from <hi>Sinai,</hi> we filled with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of adoption, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Sion:</hi> Gal. 4.25. a ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence whereof is the divers <hi>Methods</hi> that God
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115201:33"/>hath made uſe of, in delivering the <hi>Syſtem,</hi> or Rules of either diſpenſation unto both People. A 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> ſence may be this; the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle may intend by the <hi>Teſtimonie</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> in Gods Children, that <hi>Inclination</hi> and <hi>duct</hi> of <hi>Obedience</hi> which Gods Children do, (though not all of them in the <hi>ſame</hi> meaſure) feel in their hearts, ſweetning their natures, and bringing them gently to a complyable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with the Precepts of the Goſpel, and a putting their necks moſt willingly <hi>into the yoke of Chriſt, his Commandments being no whit grievous to them,</hi> 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.3. like as yokes are very troubleſome to Beaſts not accuſtomed thereto, (as the Prophet ſpeaks of the Jews, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18. <hi>I was chaſtiſed as a Bullock unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to the yoke;</hi>) but to ſuch whoſe necks have been uſed to draw in them, yokes are no way dreadful, or troubleſome. In the firſt of theſe ſenſes, the word <hi>Spirit</hi> muſt be taken <hi>perſonally,</hi> for the third Perſon in the ever Bleſſed and Glorious <hi>Trinity:</hi> in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> it muſt be taken <hi>tropically,</hi> the word not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying in the natural and proper ſenſe thereof, but yet not without example, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. in the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> ſenſe it muſt ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy <hi>metonymically,</hi> the effect of the Spirit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called by the name of him that works that bleſſed effect in the Souls of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt and ſecond of theſe ſenſes, the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> is communicated to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115201:33"/>all true Chriſtians; but in the third I know lyes the ground of your exception: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak ſomewhat afterward directly to this point, be pleaſed for the preſent to remember, that I have told you, that this inclination to obedience, the duct of the Goſpel is not alike efficacious up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the children of God, this Spirit being not given in the ſame meaſure to all the Sons of God.</p>
                  <p>As to the third branch of your Objection, (rather but one part of it) <hi>viz.</hi> the want of the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of your <hi>own</hi> Spirit, that might <hi>witneſs</hi> (together with the <hi>other</hi>) that you are <hi>the Childe of God;</hi> to give full ſatisfaction therein, we muſt inquire into 1. the meaning of the word [Spirit] in this place. 2. What the <hi>Testimony</hi> thereof is. And of 3. what <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> in a buſineſs of this Importance the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of a mans <hi>own</hi> Spirit is.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt; the word [Spirit] in this place muſt ſignify (I conceive) one of theſe two things: either firſt, ſome <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime</hi> Eſſence, preſiding in a Chriſtian, either as a <hi>Diſtinct ſubſiſtence</hi> from that, which is one of the <hi>eſſential conſtitutive principles</hi> of every man; or elſe as the <hi>Celeſtial</hi> and more <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical</hi> part of the Soul, <hi>informing, ordering,</hi> and <hi>governing</hi> the rational faculties in all <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Divine</hi> things. And in this ſenſe it muſt be conceived to have ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance with the office of the <hi>Imaginative</hi>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115201:34"/>faculty; which being ſeated betwixt the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> ſenſes and the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> conveyes the <hi>Species</hi> of all <hi>ſenſible</hi> objects to the <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual</hi> facultie, being it ſelf of a middle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, betwixt <hi>rational</hi> and <hi>ſenſible.</hi> To one of theſe <hi>ſenſes</hi> (I judge) thoſe <hi>Divines</hi> referre their opinions, who aſſert man to conſiſt of 1. <hi>Spirit,</hi> 2. <hi>Soul,</hi> and 3. <hi>Bodie:</hi> unleſs by [Soul] in this <hi>tripartite</hi> diviſion, they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand an <hi>Eſſence</hi> capable of no other offices in Man, but the performance of <hi>ſenſitive</hi> and <hi>vegitative</hi> operations. Or 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> the word <hi>[Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit]</hi> in this place may ſignify (and me thinks not at all incongruouſly) ſome <hi>excellent gift</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>infuſed</hi> from above in our Baptiſm, into the Souls of Chriſtians, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are not only made capable of <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving divine Revelations,</hi> and things <hi>above</hi> Reaſon, but likewiſe inclined, and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the performance of all thoſe things which God requires at their hands, to render them capable of obtaining the further ineſtimable degrees of his Love and Favour to Mankinde. And therefore 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> the <hi>Testimony</hi> of any mans <hi>Spirit,</hi> is that <hi>Evidence</hi> which it gives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the whole <hi>Series</hi> of his converſation, in reference to thoſe principles of Faith and Obedience which God hath given him, in his <hi>revealed Will,</hi> as the Grounds and Rules of his Practice. The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>Authentickneſs</hi> of which <hi>Teſtimony</hi> doth manifeſt it ſelf to every man, <hi>partly</hi> by the <hi>known truth</hi> of the things at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115201:34"/>which are not concealed from him, but repreſented as the things of <hi>himſelf;</hi> and <hi>partly</hi> from that power which God hath over it, not only in rectifying any Errors thereof, but likewiſe in ſhewing himſelf merciful to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward us, in ſuch things, wherein ſuch a <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony</hi> is not <hi>for,</hi> but <hi>againſt</hi> us. This <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> you (ſay you) want, becauſe you finde not any <hi>Witneſs</hi> in your ſelf that you are a Childe of God.</p>
                  <p>I conceive it is not impoſſible for your <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> to give this <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> though you have <hi>deafned</hi> your ear to it, and take it for ſome deception of fleſh and blood, or a deluſion of Satan, uſing all the <hi>Devices</hi> he can, to inſnare you in carnal ſecurity: but whether it be thus or no, I ſhall adviſe you to endeavour to <hi>elicite</hi> and call up this Teſtimony by that which is the <hi>Teſt</hi> of it: <hi>Do you continue in any wilful courſe of deliberate ſin? what know you by your ſelf? are you ſtill guilty of any of thoſe ſins which in the judgment of the Apostle render a man uncapable of any inheritance with the Children of God?</hi> if you are; then look not for this <hi>Testimony</hi> till you have repented, and amended your life; nor <hi>then</hi> neither for it <hi>preſently,</hi> until ſuch time as you have good <hi>experience</hi> of your Reſolutions, how they have held out in the time of tryal and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, and that the greateſt and ſharpeſt that in all likelyhood may happen unto you. But if you are not thus guilty (as for my
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115201:35"/>part I believe you a re not) of any <hi>mortal</hi> ſin reigning in your bodie; go to the <hi>Rule</hi> with this argument in your mouth: The <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of God</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever is born of God doth not ſin</hi> [willfully and deliberately] <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. But upon a ſtrict ſurvey of my ſelf, I finde that I do not commit any ſuch ſin. Therefore I am <hi>borne</hi> of God.</p>
                  <p>Upon the Truth of the <hi>middle</hi> Propoſition depends the validity of this <hi>Testimony</hi> of your <hi>Spirit;</hi> for the <hi>major</hi> is infallible, and the <hi>Concluſion</hi> is undoubtedly true, upon ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition that there be no ſuch ſin, either of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or commiſſion, in your converſation, which may exclude you from your Sonſhip: But yet for as much as the Apoſtle doth tell us, that <hi>though he knew nothing by himſelf, yet was he not thereby justified;</hi> we ought in reaſon to lay no more weight on this diſquiſition and ſearch of our ſelves, then it will bear: for our <hi>Knowledge</hi> being <hi>imperfect,</hi> this ſearch and inquiry into our own wayes cannot be abſolutely perfect: and conſequently we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to errors therein: yet is it moſt certain, that if we do it in ſincerity of heart, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality to our ſelves; not only, not allowing in our practiſe any the ſmalleſt ſin, but by deeds of Mortification, earneſtly, and faithfully endeavouring to ſubvert the power of it; we have the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie</hi> to rely on, in the Tenor of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, not exacting <hi>unſinning</hi> obedience under
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115201:35"/>pains of eternal death, from thoſe who ſhall be reputed, and rewarded as the Children of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECT. XV.</head>
               <p>But if I were a Childe of. God, I cannot but in reaſon expect a more <hi>compliable</hi> temper with the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then I finde in my ſelf: even to thoſe things, from which I actually do abſtain, I perceive in my ſelf moſt violent, and ſtrong inclinations; ſo that I have no Comfort from the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory</hi> over my Luſts; ſuch <hi>murmurings</hi> and <hi>regrets</hi> I have in my ſelf, for not letting looſe the <hi>Rains</hi> of my corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="21">21. MY anſwer to this Objection will likewiſe diſcharge your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of what I promiſed more fully to ſpeak, in reference to that (ſuppoſed) exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption you would have againſt your ſelf, from the third ſenſe I ſuggeſted unto you, which the Apoſtle might intend, by the <hi>Testimony</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> in that of the <hi>Romans</hi> lately men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
                  <p>It is not to be denyed by any the <hi>Greatest
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115201:36"/>Saint</hi> upon earth, but that he feels in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the <hi>Contests</hi> of <hi>two</hi> contrary Principles, <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>old</hi> and <hi>new man:</hi> and evident I preſume it is, that from hence ariſes very much of their trouble who have tender and good natures, but weak and diſordered Judgments. For <hi>first,</hi> many of thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do conclude, that all, even the <hi>first moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to ſin, which they feel in themſelves, how <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> and <hi>impetuouſly</hi> ſoever rejected by their Spirits, do yet leave ſome <hi>dangerous guilt</hi> ſticking upon their Conſciences. And 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> that the ſtate of a Chriſtian lyable to ſuch <hi>motions</hi> againſt the Law of God, ſpringing from <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt</hi> nature in him is wholly deplorable and forlorn; theſe being moſt ſure marks of his unregeneracy.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe; though there be many very judicious and pious <hi>Divines,</hi> that are of a contrary judgment acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging no more in theſe <hi>motions</hi> to ſin, then an <hi>jnfelicity</hi> accompanying the nature of the holyeſt men in this life; affording indeed matter of humility, to all the Children of God, but not aſperſing them with any guilt: yet if your judgment run along with thoſe of the <hi>other perſwaſion,</hi> I ſhall not Endeavor to alter your opinion; it being long ſince imbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed (I believe) and therefore not only diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultly changed, but allmoſt impoſſible to be cleerly eradicated out of your mind; and conſequently; may be a means not of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſening,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115201:36"/>but enlarging your Troubles: yet would I deſire you to retein your own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, with this <hi>grain</hi> of <hi>Salt,</hi> viz. that thoſe <hi>Motions</hi> are but ſins of <hi>Infirmity</hi> and <hi>Venial,</hi> which have pardon of courſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel to all the Children of God; it not being poſſible that they can live in the Fleſh, without ſuch <hi>Motions</hi> to ſin, unleſs you will ſuppoſe them capable of living in a ſtate of <hi>Impeccability,</hi> a <hi>not-ſinnable</hi> condition in this World; for that ſuch <hi>Motions</hi> muſt in reaſon be ſuppoſed to be in all perſons <hi>lapſible</hi> (as was <hi>Adam</hi> and all his Sons,) being that <hi>indelibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> ſins, as well as ſins of a <hi>ſlower fermentation</hi> in mens Souls, muſt be preceded by ſuch <hi>Motions</hi> of their Appetites, as <hi>naturally</hi> and as <hi>neceſſarily,</hi> as the <hi>colliſion</hi> of Flints muſt be before the <hi>emiſſion</hi> of fire.</p>
                  <p>As for the ſecond, ſuch <hi>Motions</hi> as theſe how vile and irregular ſoever they are, (<hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies</hi> having the ſame <hi>mint</hi> with <hi>Fornication, Adulteries, Murders,</hi> as our Saviour telleth us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19.) yet being (as we have ſaid) <hi>immediately,</hi> and with <hi>Indignation</hi> rejected by us, are no marks of an unregenerate Man, but rather the contrary: For do not we Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans engage in a <hi>warfaring</hi> life againſt the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Devil?</hi> is not the <hi>Holy man,</hi> he that leads a vertuous and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life, a <hi>Conqueror?</hi> and is there a <hi>Conqueror</hi> where there is no <hi>Enemy;</hi> have we <hi>weapons,</hi> ſpiritual ones, put into our hands, to <hi>beat the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115201:37"/>Air withall?</hi> are not theſe <hi>Motions</hi> the <hi>enmity of the Fleſh,</hi> which we are engaged to oppoſe and deſtroy, that <hi>Amalek,</hi> with which we <hi>muſt have war for ever?</hi> I mean whilſt we live in this World. And muſt it paſs for a <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Cowardice,</hi> (and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a note of <hi>Infelicity</hi>) to be dayly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with multitudes of theſe <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> which yet (like <hi>David</hi>) a valiant Chriſtian deſtroys by <hi>ten thouſands</hi> at a time? if this be that <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> and <hi>Teſt</hi> of diſcerning and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing the good from the bad, Heaven will be filled with none but Angels, and thoſe innocent Creatures, whoſe good hap it was to dye whilſt their ignorance of Good and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil (like the Children of the <hi>Ninivites</hi>) might give them undeniable pretenſions to the crown of Glory.</p>
                  <p>Should you therefore condemn your ſelf, for that ſuch <hi>Duels</hi> and <hi>Battles</hi> as theſe are dayly <hi>fought</hi> in your Breaſt, for that <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> againſt the Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Appetites, are dayly detected and prevented; the <hi>Plotters</hi> and <hi>Conſpirators</hi> ſubdued, chaſtiſed, and kept under by an high hand; ſhould you, I ſay, condemn your ſelf for this, you would in that ſentence condemn <hi>the Generation of Gods Children;</hi> the main dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>carnal</hi> Men and Women lying in this, (not that one ſort <hi>feels</hi> no conteſt with <hi>Motions</hi> to ſin, the other have Souls dayly <hi>clouded</hi> and <hi>peſtred</hi> with
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115201:37"/>ſuch <hi>Locuſts</hi>) <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16. but one of them, <hi>viz. ſpiritual</hi> Men do conquer and ſubdue, but <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Men and Women do yield to, and are van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd by theſe Luſts.</p>
                  <p>Honour and commendation are not only <hi>due</hi> to Fortitude, but do foment and cheriſh that Virtue: take you heed therefore that that be not applyable to you, which the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and wiſe <hi>General</hi> of King <hi>Davids</hi> Army foretold him upon his <hi>ſour</hi> entertainment of his Souldiers, after their Victory over <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> (the Kings <hi>Darling</hi> as much as <hi>Enemy,</hi>) 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.7. You ought to encourage your ſelf in God, and bleſs and praiſe him by whoſe Grace it is that you are thus <hi>victorious,</hi> and that <hi>for the praiſe of his Glory,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth more than <hi>once</hi> intimate in <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.12, 14.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION. XVI.</head>
               <p>But how then is my Nature <hi>changed,</hi> where is that <hi>new Creature, created after God in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs?</hi> What <hi>Renovation</hi> by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> if ſuch <hi>Motions</hi> to Sin as theſe, croud in upon the Soul of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Chriſtian? I cannot but be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it was much otherwiſe with the Apoſtle, and is ſo ſtill with Holy men, though not with me.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:115201:38"/>
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="22">22. THe <hi>Anatomy</hi> of every, or any ſingle Chriſtians Soul, with the true ſtate and poſture of his Mind you cannot <hi>certainly</hi> know, unleſs the perſon may be preſumed, not only to ſpeak truth, but throughly to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand his own condition in this point, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did. But certain enough it is, that Holy men extraordinarily inſpired by God, have grievouſly complained of the guilt of Sin, and of their exceeding great troubles for it, even to diſtraction, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 88.15. neither of which could poſsibly happen unto them, (the later being the fruit and effect of the former) with theſe <hi>precedaneous motions to</hi> fin.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, let the Thoughts, Words, and Deeds of the holyeſt perſon which you would inſtance in, be <hi>ſifted</hi> to the bottom, and ſome <hi>bran</hi> will be found in them, ſome <hi>chaff</hi> will be winowed out of the <hi>heap</hi> of his converſation; even ſince that time, that he hath had ſome comfortable aſſurance of his good Eſtate: but all this is not only tryable by experience, but by Rules and Grounds of Divinity, which have proportion with the <hi>Analagy</hi> of Faith.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. The <hi>new Creature,</hi> or the <hi>Regenerate</hi> man who doth ſincerely endeavour <hi>to perfect Holyneſs in the fear of God,</hi> doth not paſs into
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115201:38"/>this eſtate, by any <hi>phyſical</hi> and <hi>natural,</hi> but by a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>moral change;</hi> the principles of Motion and Operation in him, continuing not only the ſame, but ſtill lyable to the ſame Errors in working as before; otherwiſe (as we have already ſaid) his ſtate muſt be a ſtate of <hi>Impeccability,</hi> which was never in our earthly Tabernacle but once, when <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> took our nature upon him: in whom, though the humane nature was <hi>lapſible,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe otherwiſe he had not been <hi>made in all things like unto us, Sin only excepted,</hi> Heb. 2.17. (which <hi>lapſability</hi> is not,) yet by reaſon of the <hi>hypoſtalical</hi> union of the Humane and Divine nature in his <hi>Perſon;</hi> he could not only not fall but feel no Motion to the leaſt ſin, <hi>neither was Guile found in his mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So then, by reaſon the faculties in the Soul remain the <hi>ſame,</hi> after, as before converſion, (as that man doth <hi>will</hi> Vertue with the ſame <hi>Individual will,</hi> wherewith before he did <hi>will</hi> Vice: he doth <hi>love</hi> God with the ſame natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral power of <hi>affecting,</hi> wherewith before he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the World.) It muſt follow, that the Soul and her Appetites, as well <hi>concupiſcible</hi> as <hi>iraſcible,</hi> being ſtill phyſically the ſame; the change is only in theſe 3 things eſpecially, the 1. <hi>cauſe,</hi> 2. <hi>manner,</hi> and 3. <hi>end of their operation.</hi> The <hi>Moral</hi> cauſe, (if I may ſo term it) by the efficiency whereof the Will and her Appetites are in a Regenerate man moved to <hi>act,</hi> upon the propoſal of any object, is that <hi>Tincture</hi>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115201:39"/>of Grace, which is caſt into the Soul by the bleſſed <hi>Spirit</hi> of God: which is a kind of <hi>Principium motus &amp; quietis</hi> in Moral, as <hi>Nature</hi> is in things Natural, mingling it ſelf into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very faculty of the Soul, apprehending in the <hi>Intellectual,</hi> willing or nilling in the <hi>Elective</hi> power, governing and guiding the Affections in all their Operations, both of averſation and deſire, being ſo perfectly <hi>aſsimilated</hi> to the nature of the Soul, that (as is the Soul in which it dwells) Grace is better appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by her operation in Regenerate men, than defined in its eſſence: ſomething there is that moves them to Act, not only ſo <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to others, but even to themſelves whilſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21. (as the contrary effects of <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Shame</hi> in the ſame <hi>Perſons,</hi> flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the <hi>ſame</hi> Acts, though under a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſtate doth evidence) but to define what this is, whether a <hi>ſubſtance</hi> or a <hi>quality,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>Act,</hi> or any <hi>Aſsiſtant form,</hi> may (poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly) appear a difficulty ſo much the greater, by how much the more ſolidly it is inquired into.</p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>manner</hi> of a Regenerate mans working by Grace, it is <hi>regular,</hi> according to that order which God himſelf hath fixt in our Nature, <hi>Reaſon</hi> being the Judge of all our Actions, uncorrupted by any prepoſſeſſion, paſſion, or intereſt, which are the cauſes of all <hi>diſorderly</hi> Actions of the Soul, invading by force or ſtratagemme, the more <hi>noble</hi> and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115201:39"/>
                     <hi>rational faculties,</hi> whereby Unregenerate men are carried <hi>(vertiginouſly)</hi> about with divers Luſts, as well as with every <hi>wind of Doctrine, Eph.</hi> 4.14. which is a luſt in the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo the more dangerous, as are Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that fix themſelves in the <hi>vital</hi> parts, and in <hi>circular</hi> motion, we know that each part of the Orbe hath a viciſſitude of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority: but in the Soul of man Reaſon ought to be fixt in the higheſt ſeat, the deepeſt <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of Faith no way depoſing this <hi>Queen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> from her Dignity, but only exacting from her that <hi>Homage</hi> and <hi>Fealty</hi> which is due to <hi>Divine Revelations,</hi> and the <hi>Aſsiſtances</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> acting herein ſpiritual and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly, for the change that is wrought in the <hi>end</hi> of a Regenerate mans Actions, that which he now <hi>ultimately</hi> and chiefly aims at, is the manifeſtation of Gods Glory: and the <hi>ſubordinate</hi> end of all his Endeavours, is his own, and the ſalvation of other mens Souls: but with men of unchang'd Natures, as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in a ſtate of Corruption is the Principle from which they work, and their Manner wholy <hi>enormous;</hi> ſo is their <hi>end</hi> ever their <hi>ſelf,</hi> even in that worſer ſenſe, wherein an obedience; and captivity to all, or ſome kinds of carnal Luſts, for ſatisfaction of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and brutiſh part in them is ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in oppoſition to that <hi>manual</hi> of Goſpel-Duties, (as I may call it) abridged into
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115201:40"/>that moſt comprehenſive <hi>Notion</hi> of Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal.</p>
                  <p>Briefly then, if you will but obſerve the Principal <hi>efficient</hi> of your moral Actions, the <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of doing them, I truſt you will be able to ſee ſo great a contrariety be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe of the Unregerate, and Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate life, that you will without any juſt cauſe of doubt as freely aſſert the ſpiritual Life you lead, from the vigour and <hi>energy</hi> of that <hi>New Nature</hi> in you; as you do the Natural life you live, by the power of the <hi>Old Nature,</hi> in a <hi>phyſical</hi> ſenſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION. XVII.</head>
               <p>But me thinketh [ſay you] I may and ought to be a much better Chriſtian than I am.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="24">24. NO moral duty (like <hi>Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal proportions</hi>) doth conſiſt in an <hi>indiviſible</hi> point. That which we judge to be the worſt may yet be worſer, and that which we take to be the beſt may yet be better, if done by any Creature not impeccable. <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chue Evil, and do Good</hi> is the rule of <hi>holy living,</hi> Pſ. 34.13. which he that ſincerely doth, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not be <hi>ſcrupulous</hi> and critically inquiſitive into every ſingle Action of his Life, though he may not be remiſs and ſupine in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115201:40"/>any the moſt inconſiderable, <hi>whilſt it is in doing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="25">25. There is no <hi>Divine,</hi> that will aſſert the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of perfect and unſinning obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel: his own experience without the Authority of Saint <hi>John,</hi> will confute ſuch <hi>Magiſterial Theologie,</hi> e're it run from a pen, held by a hand of fleſh and blood. All humane Actions muſt needs carrie a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the nature of the <hi>Agent</hi> by which they are effected: in all moral Actions, the <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Agent</hi> betwixt the <hi>Spirit of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the <hi>material part</hi> of the Action is the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man, in which, and by which, as by a natural and voluntary Inſtrument, the <hi>bleſſed Spirit</hi> doth work: ſo that all <hi>moral productions</hi> muſt needs receive ſome impreſsions from the next, and immediate cauſe of their being: an Artificer never ſo skilfull, yet the defects and ineptitude of the Inſtrument by which he works, may ſomewhat abate of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the work, unleſs he can ſuppoſe the Soul of Man in all her faculties to be not only <hi>regular,</hi> but <hi>inerrable;</hi> that tranſpiercing Eye will ſind ſome <hi>flaw</hi> in the moſt orient moral Action, which a ſtate of Separation and Bliſs might have rendered that Action free from; our very Prayers and Prayſes are (undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly) not ſo perfect in this, as in the other life: and this is one reaſon, why till the day of Judgement <hi>Christ</hi> doth not <hi>deliver up the Kingdom to the Father:</hi> his <hi>Melcheſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kian
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115201:41"/>Prieſthood</hi> continuing in (my opinion) till that time, both for the Quick and Dead, that they may have their <hi>Perfect Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and bliſs in everlaſting glory: this the <hi>Church</hi> prayes for, and for what the <hi>Body</hi> prayes, the <hi>Head</hi> doth undoubtedly <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECT. XVIII.</head>
               <p>But me thinketh (ſay you) I may do more good then I do.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="26">26. COncerning the meaſure of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, if it were in Moral poſitive precepts of Gods revealed Will, there needs nothing more be ſaid, but that of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Theſe ought to be done, Matth.</hi> 23.23. But becauſe ſuch doubts or Scruples, that afflict your minde, are moſt likely to ariſe from thoſe duties, which are preſcribed only in groſs; but the <hi>Quotum</hi> or meaſure left to our own prudence to determine, as Faſting, Prayer, Alms, &amp;c. I ſhall onely inſiſt upon theſe, there being no tollerable doubt or ſcruple to be made concerning the other, which oblige <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> at all times, and in their full meaſure.</p>
                  <p>But you muſt take notice, that it is not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115201:41"/>poſſible that part cular Rules and Directions can be given to all Chriſtians, concerning theſe Duties, whereby all objections may be prevented: ſome what may be ſaid in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, which may ſerve ſo far to direct you, and all good Chriſtians, concerning theſe duties, that by obſerving them you may be left ſecure from all <hi>damnable omiſſions</hi> of any of theſe duties, and from any <hi>dangerous er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> in performing them. <hi>Faſting</hi> is a duty when enjoyned by publike lawful Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and for Chriſtian ends, and to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in a charitable manner, is an indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſable duty upon all, ſave ſuch, with whom that Authority doth <hi>actually</hi> diſpenſe, or may <hi>duly</hi> be ſuppoſed to be diſpenſable by ſuch an Authority. But for <hi>private Faſts,</hi> how frequently they are to be obſerved by every one, cannot be defined without ſome regard had to our conſtitution of Bodie, our calling, the uſual Contingencies of neceſſary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, &amp;c. which may hinder the performance, or make it impertinent to our end. <hi>Publick Faſts</hi> are leſs lyable to errors in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, than <hi>private</hi> are: one reaſon amongſt others is, becauſe the management of every one for that time, is for the greateſt part left under <hi>publick</hi> circumſtances of <hi>Time, Perſons, Place,</hi> &amp;c. which render the Duty more free from error and ſcruple in the Performance: <hi>Private aſts</hi> are ſeldom free from private faults and inconveniencies. Now becauſe the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115201:42"/>circumſtances of Complexion, Age, Sex, Contingencies, &amp;c. are ſo variable; my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, that few Chriſtians oblige them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Vow, (but under a pecuniary mulct to the poor they may) to the obſervation of weekly, voluntary faſts, making thoſe the choiceſt opportunities, when they are moſt fit for thoſe duties. The beſt conjuncture is <hi>Prayer, Faſting</hi> and <hi>Alms</hi> together, (or in thoſe who have no <hi>corporal Alms,</hi> ſome <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Largeſs</hi> to the Souls of others, which all may give) theſe ſet a price upon the Service of God, and keep our Religion from being <hi>cheap</hi> and <hi>refuſe,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>coſts us nothing,</hi> but the expence of a little time and breath.</p>
                  <p>But by this I deſire not to be thought to diſcharge the <hi>weekly dayes</hi> of <hi>abſtinence</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the <hi>Church,</hi> or to <hi>commute</hi> for them, by the obſervation of a day of your own; for I look upon the Authority of the <hi>Church</hi> you were baptized in, as <hi>uncancell'd</hi> in point of obliging you, and all others, who call your ſelves the <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Daughters</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe Cautions I ſhall recommend unto you, and others, in reference to the matter in hand. 1. The duties of our honeſt and neceſſary calling, (wherein men do undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſerve God, when orderly and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly performed) may, though not wholly ſuperſede, either out of our family, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate practiſe, any of theſe duties, yet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115201:42"/>us in the practice of them. So much time ſpent in prayer, cannot in reaſon be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, from one that ſubſiſts by his <hi>honeſt Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> as from him that lives of a <hi>plentiful Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue.</hi> 2. Diverſions and recreations ought not to govern us in of reſpect theſe duties: but if they be ſuch as require much of our time to the exerciſe of them (which I believe is not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Chriſtian principles) the ſeaſons muſt not be rob'd away from theſe duties, but from ſomething elſe, wherein we have a power to diſpenſe. I do not believe that an Hunting-Match, a Cittie-Viſit, or a Pack of Cards, &amp;c. ought to exchange and alter the fitteſt, and uſual times, and hours for prayer, (though neceſſary employments, deeds of Mercy and Charity may) much leſs abbreviate or wholly diſpenſe with the duty. 3. If it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that there be an opportunity of doing ſome dutie of Piety, (as publick Prayer or Sermon, &amp;c.) in that place where you are enjoyn'd to be an Auditor &amp; Member of the Congregation on the <hi>Lords day</hi> (or in any other place where you are, in caſe there be no <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the <hi>National Church</hi>) you may not abſent your ſelf <hi>only</hi> for ſuch Diverſions and Recreations; the reaſon is, not only for that a guilt of omiſſion, and alſo a ſcandal will follow from thence, but you may loſe an opportunity of doing, or receiving ſome good at that time, which you may not have tendred to you again. To laviſh away ones
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115201:43"/>time is a very great imprudence (beſides a ſin) in any Chriſtian; but to loſe <hi>ſeaſons</hi> and <hi>opportunities</hi> is a very great piece of guilt, as well as folly. 4. In caſe you have bound your ſelf to any of theſe, in reſpect of the meaſure and frequency, either by Vow, or promiſe, or firm Reſolution (eſpecially if by way of <hi>Revenge</hi> for former faults, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11.) by all means, be as projectual as you may in the obſervation there of: aſſuring your ſelf, that as you ſhall meet with the more and greater oppoſitions after ſuch Vow, Promiſe or Reſolution, ſo you will finde much more trouble upon the not performance of the duty ſo vowed, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or reſolved on; becauſe the duty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by becomes in its circumſtances to the <hi>hic</hi> and <hi>nunc</hi> of it, of the nature of Gods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable precepts, and the ſin of unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs is added to the omiſſion of that duty by you. 5. You need not ſcruple the <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>perſwaſion</hi> of the Perſon to whom you give in beſtowing of your <hi>Alms;</hi> if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Receiver thereof be ſuch, as by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt endeavours cannot provide for himſelf, and his Family in a way proportionable to the Dignity of mans Nature, you have a good aim to hit the mark of Charity; if nothing be probably ſuggeſted to the contrary, you may ſafely ſuppoſe any one that asketh, capable of your charitable Benevolence. 6. in giving ever have regard to that your Eye informs
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115201:43"/>you, the poor Wretch ſtands moſt in need of, and which others are not ſo likely, or ſo well able to ſupply, as your ſelf. I need not mention to you any caution againſt <hi>vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the <hi>forfeiture</hi> of your Reward in Heaven, upon our Saviours own caution againſt it, will be your daily Remembrancer thereof. 7. To conſtant Prayers and other holie Duties in your Familie, though there be no Poſitive command in Scripture for it, I believe you hold your ſelf obliged. Yet would I not have you ſo wedded to any <hi>form,</hi> as not being able to pleaſe your ſelf therein, you ſhould whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharge the Dutie it ſelf, that which beſt opens your Wants as a Chriſtian, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth home to the <hi>concernments</hi> of your own Family, is the moſt proper, and in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood may beſt ſuit with the <hi>temper</hi> and <hi>perſwaſion</hi> of everie Perſon in your Houſe; which in this Age we live in, may not be ſo unanimous, as you deſire. 8. In the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of any of theſe (as of all other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) labour to ſhew your ſelf of an <hi>alacrious Spirit.</hi> For being they are Free will Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, (at leaſt manie Acts of them may be ſo) it is true in all the reſt, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>one</hi> of them, <hi>God loveth a chearfull Giver.</hi> 2 Cor. 9.7. 9. I ſhall conclude with this caution (which I deſire you to make uſe of as a <hi>cordial,</hi> and not as a <hi>conſerve</hi> to make other things <hi>glib</hi> and <hi>palatable</hi> in ſwallowing) remember that there is great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115201:44"/>the certain puniſhment annext to the breach of Law, and a leſſer degree of Glory in the life to come, he that <hi>ſoweth</hi> plentifully, ſhall <hi>reap</hi> plentifully; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6, 7. though where there is no ſowing at all, no <hi>Harveſt</hi> (in Juſtice) can be expected, yet where there is this ſpiritual <hi>ſowing</hi> the <hi>crop</hi> ſhall be <hi>anſwerable</hi> to what is ſown. Though it ſhould be every mans deſigne, to aim at the <hi>higheſt degree</hi> of Glory, and yet believe that he deſerves not the leaſt: yet I would have ſuch as are of your <hi>ſad temper</hi> to conſider; that there is no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger incurred, by being only capable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a leſs reward then other men.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION XIX.</head>
               <p>But I think my ſelf bound in Conſcience to do the moſt and beſt I may, and therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn my ſelf of ſin, as oſt as I fail of doing that which is <hi>beſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="27">27. YOur condition may be ſuch, as that you may be utterly uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of doing that which is <hi>beſt;</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently you ought not in reaſon to think your ſelf bound to all that is <hi>beſt.</hi> A ſingle life is <hi>beſt,</hi> in compariſon of Wedlock, (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115201:44"/>the Perſon qualified for Coelibate:) yet if you are entred into the ſtate of Marriage, (though you found your ſelf capable of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving without Luſt of <hi>burning</hi>) yet you muſt now content your ſelf with that ſtate of life, and <hi>therein abide with God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.24. do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Duties agreeable, and proper to that <hi>kinde</hi> of life. But you mean (perhaps) of ſuch things as are yet in your choice; as to Pray in <hi>Canonical</hi> hours, as do the <hi>Regulars</hi> or <hi>Religious</hi> of the <hi>Roman Perſwaſion;</hi> or to give ſo much Alms, as may <hi>quadrupliate</hi> the proportion you have hitherto given, being able <hi>ſo</hi> to do. I confeſs I do not take it to be a fault, but a piece of <hi>Heroical</hi> Charity, if any one doth by this means, ſo leſſen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in reſpect of his former quality, that the <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> he formerly enjoyed as his <hi>Civil Right,</hi> (provided he be no <hi>publick Magiſtrate,</hi> which (perhaps) may alter the Caſe) the <hi>Port</hi> and <hi>Equipage</hi> of his living is thereby depreſt, and made <hi>inglorious</hi> in the eyes of <hi>worldly</hi> men. But as I take this to be no fault, but much otherwiſe; ſo I muſt take leave to ſcruple your ſcruple you raiſe from your <hi>private</hi> belief in this point; <hi>viz.</hi> that you are <hi>obliged</hi> thus do; becauſe your Conſcience tells you, you are capable of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. Your Argument ſtands thus; <hi>Such an Heroical piece of Religion</hi> I <hi>am capable of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, therefore my Conſcience tells me I am bound to perform it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115201:45"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Two</hi> things muſt here be enquired into. 1. <hi>Whether my capacity of doing that which I am not apparantly commanded to do, be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ground to inferre my obligation thereto?</hi> in caſe this be not ſo, whether 2. <hi>my belief that it is ſo, hath a power of obliging me thereto?</hi> as in matters of <hi>Indifferency.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the <hi>firſt</hi> Propoſition cannot be held for an <hi>univerſal Affirmative,</hi> may be clear to any one, from theſe two Inſtances. 1. There be divers perſons in the world, that are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of performing the <hi>Miniſterial Function,</hi> in point of <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Moral Behaviour;</hi> which yet never did conceive themſelves, nor any body elſe believe, that they were <hi>indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> bound, by this <hi>aptitude</hi> of theirs to enter into <hi>Holy Orders.</hi> I muſt confeſs that in the firſt Plantation of the Goſpel, or in an intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable ſcarcity of Miniſters, the caſe may (poſſibly) be otherwiſe; eſpecially if ſuch perſons perceive in themſelves an <hi>unuſual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition,</hi> and <hi>improvement</hi> of their abilities, under common means; and a greater <hi>violence</hi> and <hi>ſtirring of Spirit</hi> in them toward that Profeſsion, (eſpecially if under perſecution, or very ſlender encouragements to imbrace it) together with the remarkable deſires of others, that they would engage therein, (the <hi>Concurrence</hi> of which are very neer to an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Calling.</hi>) But generally I conceive the caſe to be as is afore determined. Again 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> tis clear from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. That a ſingle Life
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115201:45"/>is better, in many reſpects, then Marriage: now if a Virgin living in her Fathers houſe, ſhould finde in her ſelf <hi>no neceſſity</hi> to marry, but rather ſtrong inclinations (and for the beſt reaſon of all, <hi>that ſhe might ſerve the Lord without diſtraction</hi> by worldly buſineſs) to continue a Virgin, ſuppoſing ſhe were <hi>actually</hi> obliged ſo to do, upon finding in her ſelf this capacity of living unmarried; I deſire to know, whether her Father (if he ſees it <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> for himſelf, eſtate or Family that ſhe ſhould marrie) may <hi>compell</hi> by his <hi>Fatherly Authority,</hi> ſuch a one to accept of a fit Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, tendered to her by her Father? on the one ſide here is the Command of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; on the other (on that ſuppoſition) the Command of God; this to abſtain, that to marrie; into what a ſad perplexitie will ſuch a one be caſt, if that ſuppoſition were true?</p>
                  <p>But I deſire him that holds the firſt opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>[that his capacity of doing that which he is not apparantly commanded to do, is a ſufficient ground to inferre his obligation thereto]</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this reaſon to the contrary: the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of doing any thing, whether <hi>precedaneous, concomitant</hi> or <hi>ſubſequent</hi> to the command, is no more then a <hi>Qualification,</hi> or <hi>obediential power</hi> and <hi>paſſivity</hi> in the object, by which the Law becomes <hi>ſuitable</hi> to the Creature, to whom it is given, and without which the Command can neither be <hi>reaſonable,</hi> nor <hi>juſt</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115201:46"/>it being as diſagreable to <hi>original juſtice,</hi> that a Law or Command be given to any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Superiour</hi> to his abilities of keeping it; as it is contrary to <hi>ordinate juſtice</hi> to puniſh that Creature, for the not performance of a Command ſo given. Not the <hi>Obligency</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but the <hi>equity,</hi> or <hi>reaſonableneſs</hi> of the Law, is founded in the <hi>Capacity</hi> of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to obey it (that being indeed founded in the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of the Law-maker) other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there would be tranſgreſſion, where there is no Law, contrary to the ſaying of St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 4.15.</p>
                  <p>The main doubt behinde is, <hi>whether a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief grounded upon ſuch an aptitude, doth oblige that perſon in whom it is, to the performance of ſuch things, for which there is no particular precept given him by God?</hi> and ſo may be underſtood to be of the ſame nature with that, which <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> call a <hi>Perſonal precept,</hi> as was that of our Saviour to the young man, requiring him to ſell all, and give to the Poor, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.22. a Precept which <hi>Divines</hi> have hitherto held to be of the nature of thoſe <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> in the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> called <hi>Conſtitutiones perſonales,</hi> Inſt. lib. 1. Tit. 2. n. 6. none of which <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greditur perſonam,</hi> goes further than the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to which it is given, and therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>become not Preſidents or Examples for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, though they have <hi>Legis vigorem</hi> the force of Law, in reſpect of them to whom they are given.</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:115201:46"/>
                  <p>Therefore I anſwer, That a Perſon that thus believes, is <hi>bound</hi> by his <hi>erroneous</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or Judgement to the thing which he conceives himſelf thus capable of doing, but yet not irreverſibly <hi>bound,</hi> as that man that receives a <hi>perſonal</hi> Precept from the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver is, till the Law-giver himſelf be pleaſed to reverſe it. He then that is thus <hi>bound</hi> by the <hi>error</hi> of his Judgement, in the firſt of thoſe things controverted betwixt us, under this objection, is freed from all Obligation to performance, as ſoon as his Judgement (or Conſcience) is rectified; which is done aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon as he is perſwaded of the truth of this propoſition, viz. <hi>That the capacity of doing what is beſt, doth not render the Perſon capable obliged to do what is beſt.</hi> Wherein (I think) the reaſon foregoing will give ſatisfaction to any <hi>unprejudicate</hi> Perſon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION. XX.</head>
               <p>But doth not our Saviour diſcharge the force of your reaſon in Mat. <hi>19.12. He that is able to receive it, let him receive it;</hi> —But I am able to receive it,—therefore I am bound to receive it.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115201:47"/>
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="26">26. YOu muſt prove, that our Saviour <hi>injoyns</hi> that as a <hi>Precept,</hi> and not propoſeth it as his <hi>Advice</hi> or <hi>Counſell;</hi> otherwiſe it cannot be thought to contain in it the <hi>force</hi> of a Command; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently hath not in it the <hi>obligatory</hi> of a Law, but the perſwaſory <hi>efficacie</hi> of an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
                  <p>Now that thoſe words do not contain the force of a <hi>Precept</hi> in them, will (I believe) be evident, if you conſider the paſſage to which they are immediately related; and that is the ſaying of the <hi>Diſciples v.</hi> 10. conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Mariage to be (in point of <hi>Prudence</hi>) much worſe than a ſingle life, in caſe there ought to be no divorce of Man and Wife, ſave for Adultery only. <hi>It is not (ſay they) good to marry, if the caſe be thus;</hi> which clearly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies thus much, that it is beſt in point of <hi>prudence,</hi> (this being in every mans <hi>choyce</hi>) not to marry; to which our Saviours Anſwer is to this purpoſe, that they are in the right, if it were alike with all men in reſpect of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from Marriage; but being it is not ſo, they that cannot contein ought to marrie, but if a Man can contein, their Judgement is good, and is confirmed with our Saviours own Reſolution therein, it is beſt for him not to marry. I believe Saint <hi>Baul</hi> will give full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115201:47"/>to this ſcruple, if you read his 7th. chapter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION XXI.</head>
               <p>But is not every Chriſtian <hi>bound</hi> in <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to uſe the things that God gives him, to the <hi>beſt</hi> advantage of his Maſter?</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="27">27. BE is <hi>bound</hi> ſo to do in point of <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence:</hi> but not by any expreſs <hi>Law</hi> given by God. Now the Obligation which <hi>prudence</hi> layes upon anie man, is not in reſpect of ſuch things as are <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil;</hi> for therein there is no <hi>libertie</hi> of Election, that which is <hi>Evil</hi> being by no means <hi>eligible:</hi> but onlie concerning ſuch things as may be <hi>well</hi> or <hi>better</hi> done, either way of doing them being <hi>chooſable</hi> without guilt, becauſe there intervenes no Law, which may <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> my will, but I am left to govern my ſelf by <hi>prudential</hi> reaſons only, which amount to no more, but the <hi>modification</hi> of my <hi>Act of chooſing,</hi> whereby it is reſolved to be more or leſs <hi>prudent,</hi> not to be <hi>lawfull</hi> or <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if I chooſe that which is <hi>leaſt</hi> to my own advantage, I do no more then what
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115201:48"/>may be done, where the <hi>election</hi> of my will is not <hi>predetermined:</hi> and if that be <hi>leaſt</hi> for the profit of my Maſter, yet he having given me no other Command, than to uſe thoſe things <hi>well</hi> which he hath given me, I have obeyed his Commands who enjoined me to do <hi>ſo</hi> much.</p>
                  <p>If a Merchant ſhould deliver a large ſtock of Goods or Monie to his Factour, and ſhould ſay unto him, imploy this to my beſt advantage, in all inſtances and at every op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie your <hi>prudence</hi> ſhall judge to be fit: in this caſe the Factor is <hi>preobliged,</hi> and muſt do onlie what is beſt, elſe he breaks the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Maſter. But if his Maſter ſay thus unto him, imploy this ſtock to my <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,</hi> and your reward for ſo doing ſhall be <hi>proportionable</hi> to the advantages I receive by your Endeavours: in this caſe the Factor is not obliged by his Maſters Command, to do anic more than imploy his Maſters goods to his profit; which if he do, be it <hi>much</hi> or <hi>little,</hi> he obeys the Command of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; but <hi>prudence</hi> binds him to do the <hi>beſt</hi> he can, for the advancing and improving his Maſters Goods, becauſe his own Reward will carry its <hi>proportion</hi> to that ſucceſs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be for the <hi>better</hi> or <hi>no,</hi> the caſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponds to the latter part of this illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="objection">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:115201:48"/>
               <head>OBJECTION XXII.</head>
               <p>But how can this ſtand with mine, (and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of all Chriſtians) to love the Lord, <hi>with all my Soul, with all my mind, and with all my ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="28">28. I Do not conceive this <hi>Paramount Law inevitably</hi> infringed, by not doing <hi>every</hi> thing that we have ability of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but are not thereto expreſly required by <hi>precept.</hi> Indeed it binds the whole man to all Duties, exacted from him by Gods <hi>reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed will,</hi> and to ſubmit to, or not withdraw my obedience therefrom, for any <hi>Competitor</hi> whatever, that may pretend claim to my <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> becauſe for that time, &amp; in that thing, (if I were never ſo good a Chriſtian) my Diſobedience of Gods Law, would unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onablie condemn me of not <hi>loving</hi> Him, <hi>with all</hi> my mind, <hi>with all</hi> my ſoul, and <hi>with all</hi> my ſtrength; the demonſtration of which <hi>Love</hi> (as our Saviour himſelf reſolves) is the keeping <hi>of Gods Commandements,</hi> Jo. 14.15. if you mark it, the keeping his Commandements is the <hi>Teſt</hi> of every mans <hi>love,</hi> ſo that he that doth that; that obſerves what ever doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115201:49"/>to be Gods Commandement, is ſaid truly to <hi>love</hi> God, and that <hi>with al his Heart.</hi> So that conſequently there is left unto men a Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of expreſsing their <hi>Love</hi> to God, in ſome Acts of <hi>Heroical</hi> Vertue, proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the <hi>free-will offerings</hi> amongſt the Jews; whereby God may have occaſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, of <hi>remunerating</hi> ſuch men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his <hi>Bounty;</hi> like as the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties performed agreeable to his Law, are <hi>rewardable</hi> by his <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> You may take this Reſolution of your ſcruple in this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal way of reaſoning. The Love that Chriſt requires from his Diſciples is the Love of Him with all their Heart, with all their Mind, &amp;c. But ſuch a Love as this is expreſt by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Commandement. <hi>Ergo,</hi> The keeping of Gods Commandments is ſuch a Love as God requires from his Children.</p>
                  <p>We may adde hereto, that when a man doth ſincerely propoſe the glory of God, as the <hi>ſcope</hi> and <hi>center</hi> of all his <hi>Actions,</hi> every ſingle <hi>Act</hi> of his Life, whether <hi>civil</hi> or religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, may be interpreted as a <hi>line</hi> tending thereto; drawn from the <hi>Circle</hi> of his <hi>firſt</hi> Reſolution, and cannot be truely ſaid to be a breach of <hi>Duty,</hi> for that it tends <hi>leſs</hi> to perfection than doth <hi>every</hi> other Action of his Life; <hi>gradual</hi> Differences in <hi>moral</hi> Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (as <hi>good, better,</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi>) making no <hi>eſſential</hi> difference in the Subjects in which they are: whereas the objects of Reward and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:115201:49"/>Puniſhment, muſt be oppoſed by <hi>contrariety</hi> as are <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice,</hi> which diverſity of Degrees in the ſame ſubject are not, as well in moral, as in natural Things.</p>
                  <p>So that without forfercing your Reaſon you may believe, that you do not love the Divine Majeſtic <hi>with all your heart, with all your mind, and with all your ſtrength,</hi> becauſe you do not every thing, which ſome <hi>eminent</hi> Chriſtians have done before you, as <hi>giving all to the poor;</hi> &amp;c. ſuch <hi>high</hi> Attempts require <hi>long ſitting down,</hi> and <hi>conſidering</hi> with your ſelf, e're you ing age in them; leſt not only that happen unto you, which befel the man in the Goſpel, who beginning a <hi>building</hi> too great for his Purſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.30. and deſiſting, was deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therefore by his Enemies, but a much worſe thing, I mean the <hi>irremoveable</hi> anxiety of future life, with all the <hi>vexatious ſcruples</hi> that Satan, or a <hi>volatile fancy</hi> may caſt upon your Soul.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTI. XXIII.</head>
               <p>But I need not conteſt ſo hotly about the meaſure of holy and vertuous Actions. The Apoſtle tells me, that without <hi>Charity</hi> all is nothing worth: I cannot deny, but that I do heartily endeavour to do all the good that I may, to any one who ſtands in need thereof; but I have no aſſurance that I do it in <hi>Charity,</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:115201:50"/>and ſo all my <hi>Hay, Wood,</hi> and <hi>Stubble</hi> may periſh, when it comes to the <hi>Teſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>29. IT is no ſmall difficultie to define what that</hi> Charitie <hi>is, which you ſuſpect you want.</hi> You accuſe not your ſelf of the neglect of any good Dutie, that concerns the bodies or ſouls of men, and that as your Brethren and Partners with you in the common benefit of Redemption. You ſincerely endeavour to practiſe forbearance, are patient and not revengefull of Injuries; kind, tender and compaſſionate; as ſenſible and zealous of other mens good as of your own,; far from envying; well-pleaſed at other mens happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; hating all fooliſh elation of mind; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all pride and inſolence, in over-valuing your ſelf and deſpiſing others; you keep your ſelf from uſing others unſeemlie; either in Words or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; inclinable to take care of others Good and Safetie, and not only of your own; you fall not upon any provocation, into violent and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate diſtempers of Anger; keep account of all the Good that hath been done by any, but none of the Evil; you rejoyce not at the Errors and Sins of other men, but are paſſionately grieved for them, and contrarily made glad, by the good and holy converſation of your fellow Chriſtians; inclinable to conceal all the Evil that you know of another, ſo far as is for his Good, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the greater Good of others; you blelieve
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115201:50"/>without prejudice all the Good you hear of others? or have Ground in Charity to believe of them? you hope that you believe not, and never ſo far deſpair of their Repentance, as to give over uſing all probable means which may reclaim your wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Brethren; enduring much pain, trouble and loſs, without Regret, for the recovering of ſuch as are indangered by any unchriſtian practiſes. <hi>Now that this is that</hi> Charitie <hi>the Apoſtle ſo magnifies, you have not only the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the thing it ſelf, but the credit of a moſt</hi> learned, pious, <hi>and</hi> judicious Paraphraſt <hi>on that Chapter; whoſe very words I have tranſcribed (at leaſt the full importance of them) for your ſatisfaction in this ſcruple: preſuming that the authoritie of ſo reverend a Perſon, will fix your judgement beyond the</hi> aſſaults <hi>of anie ordinarie</hi> Temptations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I cannot therefore be ſo</hi> uncharitable <hi>to you as to joyn with you in a</hi> Verdict <hi>againſt your ſelf, for want of</hi> Charitie. <hi>I doubt not, but you have in your heart this</hi> Water ſpringing up to eternal life; <hi>though like</hi> Hagar <hi>almoſt</hi> dead <hi>by</hi> thirſt, <hi>you want an</hi> Angel <hi>to ſhew you this</hi> Fountain, <hi>Gen. 21. When ſuch fumes as theſe darken your Soul, do not ſeek for</hi> light from ſparks of your own kindling; <hi>but from the</hi> Sun of Righteouſneſs; <hi>that</hi> Light that light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth everie one that cometh into the world. <hi>Jo. 1.9.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In a word therefore, you muſt know, that when the Apoſtle thus magnifies</hi> Charity, <hi>it is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115201:51"/>the ſame thing as to comprize and exalt the</hi> whole dutio <hi>of man toward our Neighbour, in that one word; and to prefer that before the</hi> guifts <hi>of</hi> edification, <hi>whether Tongues, Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Miracles, &amp;c. the excellencie and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, or of any</hi> heroical <hi>Action, as</hi> giving ones Goods to the Poor, <hi>or</hi> ones Bodie to ſuffer Martyrdome, <hi>is not comparable to that practical Vertue, in the full</hi> latitude <hi>thereof. And this cannot but be evident unto you, if you conſider the compariſon the Apoſtle makes betwixt Charitie and ſuch Gifts, in the 12,</hi> &amp; <hi>13</hi> Chap.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION XXIV.</head>
               <p>But in all my Actions I endeavour to <hi>skrien</hi> my ſelf from the <hi>wrath</hi> of God, and to prevent his <hi>Juſtice</hi> upon my perſon for Sin already committed, perfectly indeed <hi>abhorring</hi> it as the cauſe of all my Troubles, but not truly <hi>enamoured</hi> of Vertue (me thinks) becauſe it yields me no ſuch. <hi>Harveſt</hi> of Content, and felicity as the <hi>Heathens</hi> themſelves could boast of.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115201:51"/>
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="30">30. THat your <hi>ſelf</hi> ſhould be your <hi>end,</hi> aſwell as God, is not contrary to Piety; but your ſelf muſt be put in a <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>ſubordinate</hi> place, and God in the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>chiefeſt:</hi> becauſe God, being the <hi>chiefeſt good,</hi> and our Salvation <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to his Glory, as he is in this the <hi>prime mover</hi> of our Wills, (both <hi>objectively,</hi> and <hi>efficiently</hi>) ſo conſequently muſt he be the <hi>ultimate end</hi> of our Actions.</p>
                  <p>But in this caſe we muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt <hi>what</hi> God <hi>is,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> we apprehend him to <hi>be:</hi> a Sinner is not preſently brought to lay aſide the fear of Gods revengefull hand, and to imbrace, and depend upon him, for the mercie that is offered to him. <hi>Ordinarily</hi> (I conceive God doth manifeſt his love, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and mercy to penitent Sinners, <hi>gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally;</hi> and with proportion to future experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of the truth and ſincerity of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. I mean ſuch a manifeſtation of himſelf, in theſe <hi>Attributes</hi> of <hi>complacency</hi> and <hi>benignity</hi> to Mankind; which one may term the <hi>overſhadowing</hi> of the Spirit of Love upon the Soul, inlightning, refreſhing, and comforting her, againſt the terrors of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice due to Sin without a <hi>Propitiation</hi> by Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Let me therefore adviſe you, to wait with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115201:52"/>patience till the <hi>day break, and the ſhadows flee away;</hi> Cant. 1.17. <hi>till this Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ariſe upon your Soul with healing in his wings,</hi> Mal. 4.2. and to endeavour to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (as of other mens ſo) of your own <hi>filiation,</hi> and that you may the better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, to bleſs God moſt frequently for the ineſtimable gift of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, by whom alone a Reconciliation was wrought betwixt. God and mankind; by the Faith whereof holy Men and Women look for the inheritance of Sons and Daughters, and do not ſtand in fear of ſtripes as vaſſals, and Bond-ſlaves: being emancipated from the Spirit of Bondage, through the freedom they have by the Spirit of Adoption, whereby they cry <hi>Abba</hi> Father: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 15. meditating upon the greatneſs, and excellency of that love, the <hi>ever-bleſſed</hi> and <hi>glorious Trinitie,</hi> hath expreſt unto our Souls, engraven before our eyes in <hi>eternal Characters</hi> of <hi>Blood;</hi> even the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>only Son</hi> of God largely deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by all four Evangeliſts in their Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Goſpel; though ſundry, yea innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable other paſſages of our Saviours life are omitted S. <hi>Jo.</hi> 21 (yea even the birth of <hi>Christ</hi> by two of them) intimating unto us, not only the <hi>certain truth</hi> of his Paſſion (which had been unqueſtionable if but recorded by <hi>one</hi> of them) and the <hi>great concernment</hi> of it to all mankinde, as well in the example as neceſſity thereof; but likewiſe recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:115201:52"/>by that variety of deſcribing the <hi>laſt tragical Act</hi> of his Bleſſed Life, the <hi>frequent peruſal</hi> of it in all times, and kindes of Trial, and Temptations.</p>
                  <p>What therefore you want of felicity (at preſent) and content in your <hi>New life,</hi> do not deſpair of, but expect; aſſuring your ſelf, that you ſhall one day know, and feel, that <hi>the Kingdom of God is Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rom. 14.17. God alone knowes how much of Heaven 'tis beſt to give you in this Life: that <hi>Angelical state</hi> which you aim at, might be much more dangerous for you then you imagine. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> had been rapt up into the <hi>third</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and heard things <hi>impoſſible to be uttered,</hi> becauſe he ſhould not be <hi>elated</hi> by <hi>the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Revelations,</hi> there was given unto him a <hi>thorn in the fleſh,</hi> the <hi>meſſenger of Satan,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.7. ſome <hi>humiliating</hi> Temptation, that might make him know, that as yet he was <hi>lock't up</hi> in an earthly Tabernacle, as lyable to the Aſſaults and Invaſions of <hi>Satan,</hi> and his Complices, as to a final diſſolution by death.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECT. XXV.</head>
               <p>But ſtill, me thinketh, if God had ſuch a Love to my Soul, he ſhould vouchſafe me ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:115201:53"/>thereof. St. <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyced in his Infirmities, <hi>deſiring to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt:</hi> but nothing is ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me as <hi>Death;</hi> as if I had either no <hi>Chriſt</hi> to go unto, or no ſuch <hi>Chriſt as</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="31">31. THe Conſideration of the <hi>World to come,</hi> and expectation of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of the Righteous Judgement of God,</hi> diſpenſed by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> according to the <hi>things</hi> that men have done in their bodies, whether it be good or evil, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.11.) is queſtionleſs a very terrible thing, even to ſuch Chriſtians, as ſhall never have their ſhare <hi>in the Lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone for evermore.</hi> But is it not the <hi>ſame Word</hi> of God which promiſeth a <hi>Pardon</hi> to the Penitent, and threatneth damnation to the impenitent Sinner? Why do you not believe him when he promiſeth Mercy, as well as when he threatneth Vengeance? He that believes not the <hi>Divine Majeſty</hi> in any <hi>one</hi> branch of Faith, revealed plainly in his Word, doth not believe him in the <hi>reſt;</hi> becauſe the <hi>ground</hi> of Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Veracity of God</hi> is the ſame in all: the <hi>ſame Truth</hi> in Promiſes of Mercy, as in Threatnings of Puniſhment; the <hi>ſame Fidelity</hi> in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:115201:53"/>of <hi>Good</hi> things, as in the Execution of <hi>Evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for your inſtance in St. <hi>Paul;</hi> (I think) I have already intimated unto you, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Saint of moſt eminent and exemplary piety, of a Charity and Love to Chriſt and his Church even unto <hi>Extaſie</hi> and <hi>Frenzy</hi> in the eyes of the World; you ought not to expect the <hi>extraordinary</hi> favours vouchſaf't him by Heaven. A laſs why ſhould you or I look for ſo much of Heaven to be delivered to us <hi>before hand?</hi> or elſe muſt judge our ſelves wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd in the diſtribution of thoſe <hi>heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Manſions?</hi> I am confident either of us would be well content, for ſuch an aſſurance as had St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to lye mouldring in our graves a <hi>million</hi> of years, after the <hi>reſt</hi> of our Brethren are crown'd with Glory; yea (perhaps) as long in the <hi>Refining Flames</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Purgatory.</hi> But I mention not this as the <hi>faint</hi> Ejaculations of men that <hi>live without Hope;</hi> but as expreſſions, ſuitable to a <hi>ſad Reflection</hi> upon our own Demerits.</p>
                  <p>Remember therefore, that if God think fit to give you no <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> yet he hath vouchſaf't unto you (with the reſt of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers) <hi>Promiſes of Glorification,</hi> much fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be look't after, and relyed upon, then any <hi>ſenſible</hi> and <hi>experimental Conſolation:</hi> for what is tendred to us in the Holy Scriptures, is <hi>immutable</hi> and <hi>permanent:</hi> but ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions as are drawn only from <hi>experimental</hi>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:115201:54"/>knowledge of our own obedience, are very <hi>tranſjent</hi> and incertain; never (as is the <hi>Word</hi> of God) <hi>infallible</hi> and <hi>eternal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for your <hi>Fear of Death;</hi> which you are ſo far from meeting with <hi>St. Pauls alacrity</hi> of Spirit, that you dare not encounter the thought of it in your breaſt: the ſound of a <hi>paſſing Bell,</hi> or the <hi>Sight</hi> of a Friend ſtrugling with the pains of Death, being (next to your remembrance of your own laſt end) the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midableſt thing imaginable; no queſtion the <hi>moral</hi> cauſes thereof ought to be heeded, and the <hi>effects</hi> prevented. I ſay <hi>[moral cauſes]</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I preſume there is in all creatures (men not excepted) a <hi>natural</hi> cauſe of fear of death: which may be as <hi>innocent</hi> in men, as the <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> of <hi>Joy, Delight, Grief, Anger,</hi> &amp;c. and this can no more be <hi>alike</hi> in all men in the world; then it can be imagined, there ſhould be the <hi>ſame</hi> degrees of other <hi>Affections,</hi> in all conſtitutions and complexions of men. Death without queſtion is the moſt formidable of all things in the world; being that ſtrong bridle which the hand of Providence hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the <hi>Jaws</hi> of wicked men, who elſe would (moſt of them) break out into the greateſt exceſſes of inſolency and outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous miſchief; this <hi>Great King of Terrors</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awing the moſt daring, and violent Spirits of men in the world. And of this <hi>natural</hi> cauſe of fear of death, you cannot but be thought to have you ſhare; for that neither
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:115201:54"/>your <hi>Sex,</hi> nor your <hi>Complexion,</hi> can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſeaſon you againſt the but <hi>ordinary</hi> impreſſions of that <hi>Afflictive</hi> Paſſion.</p>
                  <p>That which I have term'd a <hi>moral</hi> cauſe of this fear, I believe you already apprehend to be that (or ſome <hi>remainders</hi> of that) <hi>Spirit of Bondage,</hi> mentioned by S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8.15. which (as it ſeems by that Apoſtle) doth in nothing more fully diſcover it ſelf, then in the bitter apprehenſions of death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15. this cannot be excuſed (much leſs incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in you, or in any other; but will ſtand in need of much good counſel, and your own moſt <hi>ſinnewed</hi> endeavours to remove or leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen it.</p>
                  <p>But what is it that you fear in death? the <hi>pains</hi> thereof you cannot in reaſon fear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you know not of what, or whether of any diſeaſe you may dye: whether you may have <hi>pains</hi> or no, or <hi>ſenſe</hi> to feel them, if you have any: though even againſt theſe you are not without a Promiſe (to which I am aſſured you have as good a claim as any one) <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>God will make the merciful or Charitable mans bed in his ſickneſs,</hi> Pſal. 41.3. though when God undertakes to make the ſick mans bed, his Soul (indeed) ſhall lye much eaſier then his bodie. But that you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed fear is after death: that <hi>Thunder-clap</hi> which ſet <hi>Foelix</hi> a trembling, when it <hi>ſounded</hi> from the mouth of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> I mean, <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, Acts</hi> 24.25. which for a good
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:115201:55"/>man to fear <hi>too much</hi> is a ſigne of <hi>Puſillanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite;</hi> not to fear <hi>at all</hi> is no ſigne of <hi>Piety:</hi> our God is a <hi>Conſuming Fire,</hi> and in the beſt of us there is that <hi>droſs,</hi> which dreads the fury of <hi>Everlaſting Burnings.</hi> In a word; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other <hi>Remedies</hi> againſt the fear of death, there is none more <hi>powerful,</hi> yea ſo <hi>powerful,</hi> as the contemplation of the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which gave the fatal blow to the <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>Adamant,</hi> wherein all mankinde till then, were held captive; being indeed the <hi>death of death, Hoſ.</hi> 13.14. The <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> whereof may be (queſtionleſs) very <hi>uſefulty,</hi> as well as <hi>innocently</hi> beheld by you, or any other Chriſtians; but not under any barren and <hi>melancholick</hi> fixation of your eye or car on the ſtory of our Saviours Paſsion: but by a wiſe ſelecting out the fruits thereof, and feeding upon them by diſcreet contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, for the ſtrengthening of our inward man, againſt ſuch <hi>intimidating</hi> thoughts of Mortality.</p>
                  <p>Neither can I adviſe you to avoid any thing that may <hi>ſtirre</hi> up this paſsion of fear in your heart; but rather the contrary; I mean to be forward in imbracing any ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able opportunity of making theſe objects of ſadneſs <hi>familiar</hi> to you. For beſides that it is a duty of Religion to <hi>weep with them that weep,</hi> Rom. 12.15. <hi>to viſit the ſick;</hi> Matth. 25.36. <hi>to attend at the burial of our</hi> (not friends only, but) <hi>brethren,</hi> Tob. 2.2. yea to <hi>burie</hi>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:115201:55"/>them with our own hands, or to do any <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory</hi> office about their Corpſes, if need be: you will finde thereby this double ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, <hi>viz.</hi> that you will moſt earneſtly fly ſin, (the cauſe and ſting of death) and in ſhort time gain a great victory over this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION. XXVI.</head>
               <p>But though my <hi>fear</hi> of death be removeable, yet is not my fear of <hi>falling away</hi> from Grace to be removed.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="32">32. ANd why do you not as well fear, that the earth will <hi>open,</hi> and <hi>ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> you up <hi>quick?</hi> you have ſome dependance upon the Goodneſs and Providence of All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, that he will not thus deal with you; if you had not, your fear of the <hi>later</hi> would be as juſt, and as irremoveable as of the <hi>former.</hi> For what aſſurance have you againſt the <hi>one,</hi> that you have not againſt the <hi>other?</hi> are not the <hi>Souls</hi> of men as pretious in the Eyes of their <hi>Creatour</hi> and <hi>Redeemer,</hi> as are their bodies? can there be ſo great and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious a judgement happpen to the <hi>Bodie</hi> of any man, as is Gods <hi>total</hi> and <hi>final</hi> withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Grace from his <hi>Soul?</hi> and have you
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:115201:56"/>not the ſame <hi>Good Word</hi> of God to depend upon in your fears of the <hi>one,</hi> as well as of the <hi>other? Doth God take care for oxen?</hi> doth he give and perform promiſes of <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Rayment,</hi> and <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> &amp;c. unto the <hi>Bodie,</hi> but is he a <hi>dry</hi> and a <hi>barren Wilderneſs</hi> (as the Prophet expreſſeth it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.31.) unto the <hi>Souls</hi> of his People? I ſhall leave you to ruminate on that Argument of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 8.32. <hi>He that ſpared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all; how ſhall he not with him alſo freely give us all things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Remember, I pray, that God <hi>takes</hi> his Grace from no man, who doth not <hi>abuſe</hi> it. The <hi>Talents</hi> were <hi>taken</hi> from none, but him who <hi>wrapt one up in a Napkin:</hi> from him it was taken away indeed, and that juſtly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he made no uſe of that, which was not only intended for <hi>uſe,</hi> but would have been increaſed by <hi>uſing.</hi> He could not help indeed the <hi>taking</hi> it from him, when God for his <hi>Sluggiſhneſs</hi> thought this the moſt proper puniſhment for the <hi>one,</hi> and reward for the <hi>other,</hi> upon their Reckoning for the <hi>Talents;</hi> but by <hi>Induſtry</hi> he might have prevented it, as did the other <hi>two</hi> Servants.</p>
                  <p>And to render you ſatisfyed with an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and full paſſage of Scripture, be pleaſed to peruſe that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Hebrews, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.15. where after he had ſpoken of <hi>falling away,</hi> and the dreadful and irrecover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able eſtate of <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> he addes, that <hi>he is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:115201:56"/>perſwaded better things of them, and ſuch as are ſeen only in good Chriſtians;</hi> and his ground of that no fear is, for that God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their former labour of Love with the grace of perſeverance, the <hi>due</hi> reward of ſuch (as like you) do make <hi>uſe</hi> of Grace giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, as our Saviour witneſſeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.29.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECT. XXVII.</head>
               <p>But ſenſible alteration in me, and the <hi>Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> effects of <hi>Converſion,</hi> I finde none.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="33">33. <hi>COnverſion</hi> ſounds not the ſame thing come as it did to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Heathen,</hi> in the Apoſtles times, and after the <hi>firſt</hi> Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Goſpell, who are not only to ſuffer a <hi>Change</hi> in point of <hi>morall practiſe,</hi> but in <hi>point</hi> of <hi>belief.</hi> Neither are there any <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> gifts of tongues, and <hi>Miracles,</hi> or <hi>Healings, &amp;c.</hi> to be powred out upon <hi>new Converts,</hi> for confirmation of Faith, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of believers. When the <hi>Jewes</hi> were come into the promiſed Land, <hi>Manna</hi> ceaſed, we are now in a way of ordinary diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and though the Holy Ghoſt be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>this,</hi> as well as of the <hi>other;</hi> and our
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:115201:57"/>ſubmiſſion to <hi>this,</hi> as deeply exacted, yet is the <hi>Method,</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of the <hi>oeconomie,</hi> in ſome ſort <hi>changed,</hi> (at leaſt in the <hi>acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> parts thereof;) experience of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Faith of former ages, being argument enough to convince any rationall Souls, of the truth of it.</p>
                  <p>Such <hi>extraordinary</hi> gifts, I ſuppoſe you will not look for; but if for an <hi>extraordinary</hi> change, in your minde (though this may be thought ſuperfluous) yet do but ſet <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> from ſin, againſt <hi>Continuance</hi> in ſin, <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi> againſt <hi>Rebellion, Righteousneſs</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Sin,</hi> a <hi>Child of God</hi> againſt a <hi>Child of Wrath, Heaven</hi> againſt <hi>Hell,</hi> the <hi>Fellowſhip of God and his Holy Angells,</hi> againſt the <hi>Companie</hi> of Divels and Wicked men, <hi>Eternall joyes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Eternall torments,</hi> and the alteration is viſible enough. But if the <hi>Way</hi> bringing of you into this, muſt have been by <hi>miracle,</hi> as was the converſion of St. <hi>Paul.</hi> or with an <hi>audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble voice,</hi> as was Gods Revelation of himſelf to <hi>Samuel:</hi> the weakneſſe of this expectation betrayes it ſelf, by the <hi>ſingularity</hi> of it, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with it a ſecret condemnation of the Stupidity, of other Chriſtians, who go hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wink't they know not whether, never think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on any ſuch ſenſible <hi>Epiphanie,</hi> and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to their Souls.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="objection">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:115201:57"/>
               <head>OBJECT. XIII.</head>
               <p>But the <hi>root</hi> of <hi>Bitterneſs,</hi> from which moſt of theſe Doubts, Scruples, and Feares do ſpring is my <hi>Aptneſs</hi> to fall into ſin; together with ſuch horrible thoughts Startling up in my Heart that I could even teare that Body to peices, and rend out the Soul that harbours, and <hi>Evaporates,</hi> ſuch black, and Stinking <hi>Eruptions.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="34">34. IF the ſins you have formerly bin guilty of, are <hi>ſins of wilfulneſs,</hi> and the Relapſe, you may be thought to intend in your objection, be into <hi>ſuch</hi> ſins; then is your caſe ſo much the more dangerous, by how much the more certain it is, that ſuch <hi>ſins of Wilfulneſs</hi> are not reconcilable to a State of regeneracy. The determination whereof, I muſt referr to the Judgment of him, with whom you ſhall think fit to intruſt the <hi>Anatomie</hi> of your ſoul. But if they are but ſins of <hi>Humane,</hi> and <hi>Perſonall</hi> infirmity; then ſhall I offer to your conſideration, theſe two things: Firſt, that it being ſuppoſed that the ſins you mention, are only <hi>ſins of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirmity;</hi>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:115201:58"/>that Relapſes into <hi>ſuch</hi> ſins, are no <hi>new</hi> thing to <hi>every</hi> Child of God. as being <hi>Spotts</hi> ſo inſeparable from a State of mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that the Spirit of God hath Styled them by the mouth of <hi>Moſes, the Spots of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Deut. 32.5. aly. that it is not to be expected, that there ſhould be an <hi>Equality,</hi> of the Number or <hi>Kindes</hi> of theſe ſins, in all the Children of God; ſome being guilty of more, ſome of fewer; ſome of more of one kinde, of <hi>ſins of infirmity;</hi> ſome of another; and <hi>much</hi> of this not only depending upon the diverſity of the meaſure of grace given; but likewiſe upon the <hi>different</hi> complexions, and <hi>former</hi> habits of thoſe Chriſtians, before their Penitence and Reformation.</p>
                  <p>But if the caſe be of <hi>other</hi> Sins, viz. of <hi>Sins of Wilfulneſs,</hi> then obſerve, that there is a very conſiderable difference (at leaſt in your apprehenſion perhaps) betwixt the <hi>aptneſs,</hi> or <hi>facility,</hi> of falling into Sin, and <hi>actuall</hi> relapſing thereinto. You finde (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance) the temptations are frequent and ſtrong upon you, and your enemie very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigable and reſtleſs; and you fear that the <hi>battery</hi> in the end, will be too forcible for the <hi>fortification</hi> to hold out againſt it is that theſe <hi>aſſaults</hi> of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>bloud,</hi> will not only <hi>Storm,</hi> but <hi>take,</hi> or elſe <hi>ſurpriſe</hi> your Reſolution: but all this while, this is but anxiety: and if thoſe temptations do get ground of you; draw your will to ſome
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:115201:58"/>ſhort <hi>parly</hi> with them, and thereby increaſe your fear of <hi>Yealding</hi> to this enemy; yet is there no relapſe: and if there were, yet ought you to have conifort, againſt tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to diſpair of <hi>finall</hi> victorie: becauſe theſe <hi>utmoſt</hi> endeavors of yours together with your grief conceived for but inclining to theſe temptations, will render your conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on commiſerable in the eyes of your tender, and compaſſionate Father: who will in the end, make his <hi>strength</hi> to be ſeen in your <hi>weakneſs;</hi> giving you good reaſon to aſcribe, the cauſe as well as the honor of the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to him alone, by whom <hi>you ſhall be able to do all things. Phil.</hi> 4.13.</p>
                  <p>But to prevent your danger by temptation you ſhall do well, to open your condition <hi>freely</hi> to ſome <hi>Grave, Pious, Diſcreet,</hi> and <hi>Learned Divine;</hi> one well ſeen in the <hi>Studie</hi> of mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> (a great <hi>rarity</hi> I muſt tell you amongſt Proteſtants,) to have <hi>often</hi> conference with him, to confeſſe freely to him, to receive <hi>directions</hi> from him, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting your guilt and trouble, to <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> frequently: the <hi>bleſſed Sacrament</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>ſpeciall deſignation,</hi> for thoſe in your condition, refreſhing of wearied Souls be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great intendment of that Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Chriſts</hi> death: All <hi>temptations</hi> under ſuch <hi>hard</hi> uſage as is now preſcribed, will wither away, and dye in their prime; which by our private endeavours of <hi>eradication,</hi> do
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:115201:59"/>moſt times exceed our fears, as well as our expectations, in the growth of them.</p>
                  <p>As for the other part of your objection, wherein you complain of the depravity and corruption of your nature, belcht out many times in <hi>Prodigious</hi> thoughts of your heart, (it may be againſt the <hi>goodneſs,</hi> or <hi>juſtice,</hi> or perhaps againſt the very <hi>eſſence</hi> of the <hi>Divine Majestie,</hi>) the more holy you deſire to be, the more grievous will ſuch thoughts (as you call them) be unto you. Therefore be pleaſed to conſider, 1. that in my judgment, many of theſe are not your <hi>own thoughts,</hi> or <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of corrupt nature in you, as you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; but really <hi>injections</hi> of Satan, ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſavouring of malice againſt God, and the merciful work of our Redemption. This Itake to be it, which is called the Divells <hi>putting</hi> of ſomewhat into mens hearts, as he did the <hi>treaſon</hi> of Judas, the prevarication of <hi>Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> and <hi>Sapphira, Davids</hi> numbring the People, and St. <hi>Peters effeminate ſuggeſtions</hi> to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, &amp;c. Theſe ſometimes are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for ſin either in our ſelves or others, ſometimes only trialls from God, for the manifeſtation of the power of his Grace, in mens ſouls: and I ſuppoſe they are not duly ſtyld our thoughts, till they are admitted, and treated by us, they then become our finfull thoughts, aſſoon as we incline to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r ace them. And 2ly. I doubt not, but ſuch as theſe may be injected into
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:115201:59"/>holy men, as in the caſe of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> as we have inſtanced before. Yea and not ſo only but they may be hardned to, and imbraced, and conſequently, their ſtate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered till renewed again by faith and Repentance.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore if you reject, and not own them; grieving for them as puniſhments for ſin, praying againſt them, and perfectly hating them, with what e're is the Author of them, having an holy jealouſie over your own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, labouring to ſhut the Den of your heart againſt ſuch intruders, and to give the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>conſiderable fort</hi> to better <hi>friends</hi> to <hi>your</hi> ſalvation; <hi>you</hi> are not hereby endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by preſent guilt, or engaged under juſt fear of <hi>Apostacy;</hi> your ſtate in this (as in all other things) being not without example in the deareſt Children of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="objection">
               <head>OBJECTION. XXIX.</head>
               <p>But God hath manifeſted his Diſpleaſure againſt me in many <hi>accidents</hi> of life.</p>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>SOLUTION.</head>
                  <p n="35">35. IT may be Gods <hi>not giving you Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> is principally intended by you in this objection: the Key of the wombe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:115201:60"/>(as the Hebrewes were wont to ſay) in the Hands of God, there being indeed a more <hi>immediate</hi> coucurrence of the <hi>Divine Majeſtie</hi> required to the fruit thereof then to the <hi>production</hi> of other things in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courſe of Providence. I have known this prevaile very farr with ſome of your ſex, <hi>heightning</hi> their perplexityes from that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.15. from whence they conclude, that if a Woman continue <hi>barren</hi> in a ſtate of Marriage, there is no hopes of her ſalvation; that depending <hi>ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily</hi> upon the former condition of <hi>Child-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to this we anſwer by theſe degrees.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is no <hi>mark</hi> of Gods <hi>irreverſible</hi> anger againſt us that many <hi>Croſſe</hi> accidents befall us in this life; ſeeing they are generally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, to be not only matter of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to our Souls, bettering us by ſuch chaſtments? but they ought to be apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as <hi>Signatures,</hi> or <hi>Marks</hi> of our adoption; St. <hi>Paul</hi> having <hi>illegitimated</hi> all ſuch as are not own'd by God for ſons by theſe fatherly Corrections of them <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.8. very farr are they too from being <hi>diſtinctive prognoſticks,</hi> of thoſe everlaſting diſtributions, at the day of judgment, in the opinion of King <hi>Solomon;</hi> who tells you that, <hi>no man knoweth either Love or Hatred by all that is before them. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</hi> 9.1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Where God hath <hi>given Children,</hi> and by ſome evill accidents taken them away,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:115201:60"/>there may more juſtly be ſuppoſed a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of Gods heavy diſpleaſure, then where he <hi>gives no Children at all:</hi> yet that hath been the caſe of many (holy Men and Women, as appears in the example of <hi>Job.</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> whoſe Hiſtories are furniſht with moſt remarkable paſſages to this purpoſe, their lives being <hi>chequered</hi> (as one may ſay) with various contingencies of good and evill.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Be it granted that <hi>barrenneſs,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jewes</hi> was reputed a <hi>curſe,</hi> and that God threatneth it as a judgment upon them to have <hi>miſcarrying wombs,</hi> and <hi>dry breaſts.</hi> yet ought it not to have that Character with us Chriſtians, who are not engaged to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by promiſes of <hi>temporall,</hi> but of <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> and <hi>eternall</hi> bleſſings: things of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment even in thoſe dayes, (clouded with ſhadowing and carnall ordinances,) that God himſelf propoſes them to the obedient <hi>Eunuches,</hi> as a full (indeed ſuperabundant) ſatisfaction for their <hi>Sterility, Iſ.</hi> 56.5. the truth is, there ought not to be (neither is there without our own fault) any <hi>barrenneſs</hi> in Chriſtians of either ſex, the forming of <hi>Christ</hi> in their Souls (intimated by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, Gal. 4.19.) being a <hi>miſticall birth</hi> in all the Sons and Daughters of God; and not without ſome reflection on this, did the <hi>Church</hi> appoint the <hi>Magnificat,</hi> of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Virgin, to be publikely ſung in her <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie;</hi> it being hoped that every member
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:115201:61"/>thereof, would conſider, that they were bound <hi>to bring forth this fruit unto God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Laſtly, for that of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> the ſenſe is ſo obvious, and that falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation ſo remote from the wiſdome, goodneſs, and truth of God; that it is ſtrange the <hi>Fancies</hi> even of women (who 'tis confeſt are very forcible) ſhould be able by any <hi>chimiſtry</hi> of imagination, to extract ſuch a diſproportionall meaning from that text. For St. <hi>Paul.</hi> having fixt that ſex, in their due place of ſubordination in the Church; that he might give them ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be content with that portion, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the <hi>order</hi> of their Creation, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being not only formed <hi>after Adam,</hi> as that ſignifies <hi>order</hi> of time, but of Nature alſo, (the Man being as one may ſpeak the <hi>firſt running</hi> of the <hi>metall</hi>) and her being <hi>firſt</hi> in the tranſgrſſion, (a token of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and frailty) as the Grounds upon which he builds a <hi>concluſion,</hi> or <hi>canon</hi> for the <hi>order;</hi> not ſo likely to ſtand faſt, upon the bare authority even of the Apoſtle himſelf without being <hi>cemented</hi> and <hi>crankt</hi> with very good and undeniable reaſons. but yet, not to leave them under the diſhonour of being <hi>firſt</hi> in that fatall Crime, (Ringleaders in Rebellion ſeldome taſting, of that mercy which is ſhewed to their followers) and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to keep them from being chruſt out of that place, by the anger and inſolence of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:115201:61"/>the other ſex, the Apoſtle tells them that by the fruit of their Womb they made amends for the miſeries and miſchiefs of their fault; the <hi>Remedy</hi> comming by them (namely the <hi>incarnation</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi>) as well as the <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> of the efficacy whereof they were likewiſe to have their part if they ſhould <hi>continue</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for me the conditions of that mercifull Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; the Apoſtle very ſeaſonably mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, of <hi>conſtancy</hi> in their profeſſions, and Practiſe: of which the <hi>firſt</hi> of that ſex, ſhewed no good example, in her hearkning to the ſuggeſtions of the Serpent in Paradiſe.</p>
                  <p>More (perhaps) might be ſayd to this purpoſe, but the apprehenſions I have of your abilities and <hi>art</hi> of diſcerning, beyond the common capacity of your ſex, having already check't me, for falling into this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne, and foreſeen <hi>Digreſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus, <hi>Madam,</hi> have I given you my thoughts, in theſe generall, and conjecturall applications hopeing that they may poſſibly light on the whole, or ſome part of the <hi>cauſe</hi> of your trouble. I have offered them to you, not ſo much in acknowledgment of thoſe favours, I have heretofore received from your ſelf, and your dear Husband (ſince with God) (though my obligation, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by could not be diſcharged, by a farr great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er attempt to recompence them) as for the tender reſpect I have to your afflicted ſtate. That this ſhould do a perfect cure (though I
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:115201:62"/>know God doth (manie times) <hi>great</hi> things by <hi>ſmall</hi> meanes,) I have no <hi>grounded</hi> hopes to believe: not only becauſe of the <hi>defects,</hi> and <hi>impotence</hi> of my endeavours, but for that <hi>difeaſes</hi> of this kinde, are <hi>influenced</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the diſtempers, or complexion of the <hi>Patient,</hi> and have a <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>maligne aſpect</hi> upon them from many circumſtances, not gueſſable (I preſume) by perſons more A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, then I can deſerve to be thought.</p>
                  <p>I know <hi>Divines</hi> ſhould not undertake to cure, like <hi>Empericks,</hi> by <hi>Gueſſes,</hi> and at <hi>ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> and therefore, <hi>madam I</hi> have not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely intimated, my deſire unto you in this Paper to make a very ſeaſonable and home addreſs to ſome <hi>one of a Thouſand,</hi> Job. 33.23. A skilfull <hi>Phiſician</hi> of Souls; that you may not be thought, to <hi>ſubordinate</hi> the care of your better, and eternall part, to that <hi>Cabinet</hi> of <hi>beautifull earth,</hi> wherein God hath lock't up that <hi>rich Jewell</hi> for ſome few years: <hi>I</hi> am confident <hi>Madam,</hi> it is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the beſt, but the only Counſell you can follow, with aſſurance (by Gods bleſſing) of <hi>cureing</hi> theſe <hi>wonnds</hi> in your Spirit: no if I have but <hi>cleanſed</hi> and <hi>Wip't,</hi> or done the leaſt other good office, of <hi>helping</hi> forward their <hi>cure;</hi> as <hi>I</hi> ought (and you) to give all the Prayſe thereof to God, ſo ſhall it be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed a plentifull Reward, for this little <hi>Labour</hi> of <hi>Madam,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your affectionate Servant in</hi> Chriſt Jeſus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:115201:62"/>
            <head>A PRAYER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Allmighty God, the Creator and Preſerver of Humane Spirits, the ſearcher of all Hearts, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and tryeſt all our wayes, and underſtandeſt our thoughts afarr off: from thy love and bounty it is, and not from our deſert, that we have any meaſure of grace, whereby we may know, and obey thy Will, any impreſſion of Godly ſorrow, when we have broaken thy lawes, any deſire to reſolution and performance of what is pleaſing in thy ſight, after we have erred and ſtrayed from the pathes of thy commandments: mercifully I beſeech thee to behold all ſuch as are grieved, oppreſt, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed in Spirit, through the guilt of ſin, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Grace, frailty of Nature, or the devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our grand enemie, and accuſer. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially be mindfull of thy Servant B. B. who hath aeſired the prayers of me thy moſt unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and grievous finner. O Lord, to thee
<pb facs="tcp:115201:63"/>are known all the cauſes, and accaſions of her trouble and confuſion of Spirit; the diſtractions and terrors of her ſoul, are not hid from thine Eyes: O thou that haſt the Balm of Gilead, the Soul-healing Oyle of mercy, and pardon of ſin, pour the ſame I moſt humbly beſeech into her wounded Spirit, bind up this bruiſed Reed, kindle this Smoaking Flax, preſerve her from the Snares of Satan, free her from the deluſions and errors of a deceitfull imagination, and vouch chaſe to her ſuch a meaſure of Spirituall Conſolution, that her ſoul may be comforted and ſtrengthned thereby; to the finiſhing of her courſe with joy, through a finall Victorie over all her Enemies, by the goodneſs and power of Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:115201:63"/>
            <head>Books Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Garthwait</hi> at the little North door of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>B. <hi>Chappels</hi> Methodus Concionandi. 120</item>
               <item>—Notes upon 103. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> being a Praxis upon that Method. 80</item>
               <item>A Commentary on the 5 Books of Moſes or <hi>Pentateuch</hi> by <hi>J. Trap.</hi> 40</item>
               <item>Remains of Mr. <hi>Geo. Herbert.</hi> late <hi>Orator</hi> of the univerſity of <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reliquiae Wottonianae,</hi> A Collection of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable pieces of that great Maſter of Language and Art. Sr. <hi>Henry Wotton</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Provoſt of <hi>Eton. &amp;c.</hi> 120</item>
               <item>The <hi>Works</hi> of that profound Divine Dr. <hi>Tho. Jackſon</hi> Preſ. of <hi>Gorp. Chr. Col. Oxon.</hi> in folio. in 3 Vollumes.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Coſins</hi> Scholaſticall <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Canon</hi> of the Scripture. 40</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Waltons</hi> Introduction to the Oriental <hi>Languages.</hi> in 120</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Steward</hi> Sermon at <hi>Paris</hi> of <hi>Hezekiah's</hi> Reformation. 120</item>
               <item>The Converſion of <hi>Rigep Dandulo,</hi> a Turk, to the Chriſtian Faith, by Mr. <hi>Gunning.</hi> 80</item>
               <item>The <hi>Rationale</hi> on the Book of <hi>Com. Prayer,</hi> by <hi>Mr. Sparrow.</hi> 120</item>
               <item>The <hi>whole Duty of Man.</hi> A Book neceſſary for all Families 80</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:115201:64"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr. Joſeph Mead</hi> his Diſsertationum <hi>Triga.</hi> 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr. Dees</hi> Actions and Conferences with Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits &amp;c. Set out by <hi>Dr. Caſaubon.</hi> folio</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>School Books.</head>
               <item>Mr. Walkers <hi>Treatiſe of Engliſh Particles. 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. Busbies Horat. Caſtigat.</item>
               <item>Mr. Busbies Juvenal. Caſtigat.</item>
               <item>Mr. Busbies Perſius. Caſtigat.</item>
               <item>In uſum Scholae Weſtmonaſter.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
